<story>
<body>Chapter 32: Brahmanas repent

 

Krishna and Balarama went in the company of their cowherd friends as usual to the meadows with their cattle. They drifted far deep into the forest. On their way back, the cowboys were overcome by hunger and thirst. Krishna sent them to the brahmanas performing the angirasa sacrifice nearby. He had advised them to tell the brahmanas that Krishna and Balarama had sent them. The boys went and begged for food telling the brahmanas from where they had come. The brahmanas turned a deaf ear to the boys. They returned hungry


Brahmana wives serve food to cowherd boys

Knowing the good nature of the brahmana wives, Krishna sent the boys to them. Krishna was sure of the affectionate treatment his friends would receive. The wives of the brahmanas fed the boys to their satisfaction. The women also came to the two brothers, with platters laden with a grand feast. They considered themselves fortunate to get an opportunity to offer food personally to Lord Hari. Absolutely content with their service to the Lord, they now returned to reality. They were afraid of going back as they expected the husbands to disclaim them for disobedience. The women, in their excitement to serve the Lord, had ignored to bother about the consequences. They conveyed their fear to Krishna. Go back without any fear of ill treatment. The sacrifice, in which your husbands are engaged, would be completed without a hitch, said Krishna encouragingly.
 
             The women on return were surprised to see an unbelievable alteration in their husbands.The brahmanas were cursing their unpardonable behaviour towards the cowherd boys, who were none other than the Lord in human form. Greed for material prosperity had driven them away from meritorious deeds. All their study of the Vedic scriptures appeared futile as they had failed to see the Lord dwelling inside their very hearts. The women, who were not permitted to study the Vedas, were intellectually far superior to their privileged husbands. Even though belated, the brahmanas repented for their sinful conduct of indifference to the greatness of the Lord and begged Krishna for deliverance.

 

 </body>
</story>