<story>
<body>Veda Vyasa was the son of Parashara and Satyavati born on an island. His complexion was very dark at birth. So he was named Krishna Dvaipayana. Krishna means dark and Dvaipayana is, born on an island. He was popularly known as Veda Vyasa, a title conferred on him, as it were, for simplifying the study of the Vedas. He systematically compiled the Vedas which were orally transmitted in the olden days. Moreover, he wanted to preserve the ancient scriptures, the golden treasury of spiritual knowledge, for posterity. Author of the Puranas and the epic Mahabharatha, Vyasa had the extraordinary power of knowing the past, present and future. His Mahabharatha contains all aspects of conduct, good and bad, depicted through various characters. It is easy for even the unlettered common man to comprehend the injunctions contained therein. An analytical study would facilitate one to carve out ones personality in a virtuous way. These practical guides are not new but are coming down to us from the Vedic period. The need for writing the epic was felt because the Vedas were exclusively for intellectuals and men. Vyasa wanted the profound truths contained in the Vedas to reach everyone. Knowledge is universal to be shared and benefited by one and all. That is why this epic is  designated as the fifth Veda, as the original Vedas are four in number.

      Despite such varied accomplishments, Vyasa was obsessed with a feeling of incompleteness and a lurking confusion. While Vyasa was restless at not knowing the cause for the mental dissatisfaction, he chanced to come across the divine sage Narada, the son of Brahma. Knowing the distress of Vyasa, Narada explained the lapse in his literary efforts. He told Vyasa that he had dealt with almost all subjects under the sun but had overlooked what was crucial for attaining spiritual contentment. He went on to explain, "You have not sung the glories of Lord Krishna, son of Devaki and Vasudeva, which indeed is the summum bonum of life. That it would elevate you to Himalayan heights of bliss, you may be sure. Without loss of time, engage in writing about the glorious feats of the Lord that would help you get over your depression." Thus the Bhagavata Purana came to be written on the divine sage's advice. Besides the detailed delineation of Krishnavatara, this wonderful book contains a comprehensive narration of all the avataras of Vishnu.

       {The avataras of the Lord so far are : Matsya [fish], Kurma [tortoise], Varaha [boar], Narasimha [lion-man], Vamana [dwarf], Parashurama [vanquisher of kshatriyas], Rama [killer of Ravana], Balarama [elder brother of Krishna], and Krishna [son of Devaki]. The last of the ten avataras is believed to be Kalki yet to take place in the Kali-yuga. }

 

     Dashavataram

Narada wished to convince Vyasa that his words were gospel truth and not mere empty words inspiring false hopes. He went on to narrate the story of his previous life to substantiate the fact about the enduring happiness attained by singing, hearing and meditating on the Supreme Lord.

       Narada was born to a servant maid in his previous birth. During monsoon, some brahmanas who had mastered the Vedas, had stationed themselves at a certain place. Narada's mother served them during their sojourn. She engaged her son, yet a child, in the service of the sages. Dedicated to his work, the boy did not miss the carefree childhood enjoyed by the children of his age, in absolute abandonment, free from any kind of responsibility. The sincerity in his work earned him the love and affection of the brahmanas. One day, he partook the left over food in the platter of the brahmanas with their due permission. It instantly worked wonders on his personality development and improvement of his mental faculty. He felt as if his entire body was cleansed of its sins. The purified mind was steadily drawn towards the pious practices of the rishis. Continuous hearing of the chanting of the Lord's glories inspired devotion in his heart. In a momentary revelation, he experienced an identity with the Lord. The unusual vision wiped out his ignorance in a flash. While he was grooming himself to follow the path shown by the rishis, the monsoon came to an end and it was time for the sages to move on to a different destination. Narada, however, received a parting gift from the rishis. They imparted the secret impenetrable knowledge as revealed to them by God himself. It was now clear to Narada that life dedicated to the Lord, purged of greed and sin, would know no physical miseries, mental afflictions or suffering from calamities caused by supernatural forces.

        After the departure of the rishis, Narada stayed with his mother in a brahmana's house. Financial constraint and lack of freedom in servitude incapacitated his mother from providing her only son any facility for intellectual pursuit. Narada, engrossed in meditation, felt tied down by his mother's affection. Yet he did not have the heart to forsake her to satisfy his personal ambition. Soon after, her death by a snake bite, did not grieve him much. He took it in a stoic way as the Lord's blessing in disguise.

        Free from any kind of encumbrance, Narada decided to proceed to the north. We might wonder why the young boy chose the northern direction. What could have prompted him for his choice? Learning at the feet of the rishis guided him. In the days of yore, people with a pure heart, called the paramahamsas, resorted to the serene peaceful surroundings of the Himalayas in the north, away from the humdrum of the towns and cities. Taking to the life of a recluse, they engaged in rigorous penance there and strived hard to attain immortality through communion with God. Though he was just a boy of five years, Narada was undeterred by the arduous journey ahead. He walked across many fertile lands and finally found himself on the outskirts of a dense, dreadful forest. The dark forest looked impassable with ferocious animals like lions and tigers prowling around. The boy mustered up courage to enter the forest. He was exhausted after the long strenuous journey. Overcome by thirst and hunger, Narada's legs refused to budge any further. Taking a dip in the cool water of the river nearby, the refreshing water allayed his thirst and hunger also. He was so enervated that he lay down under a banyan tree to recuperate his strength and energy.

        Relaxing, he slid into transcendental meditation when Lord Narayana obliged Narada with a glimpse of his divine form. Elated over the extraordinary experience, he wished the thrilling vision to continue for ever. But it was not to be so. To the disappointment of the youngster, the ecstasy was over in a fleeting moment, never to be again. The Lord spoke to the depressed Narada in order to console him, lest he be discouraged. He said, "My dear child! Do not feel dejected. It was a special privilege that I appeared before you at your tender age. Such favour is not extended by me to saints even after repeated attempts. This unique gesture on my part was to encourage your dedicated devotion towards me to be sustained. Association with devoted saints will improve your unflinching faith in me and steer you away to complete freedom from the worldly distractions. When the time comes for you to leave this world, you will relinquish your mortal body, permanently uniting with me in my abode from where there is no return." With these words, the voice of God ceased. Then Narada continued his narration to Vyasa. He said, "Thereafter, my mind was solely directed towards singing the sanctifying glories of the Lord. True to his word, the Lord brought about a deluge that consumed the entire creation. I saw the Lord lying on the surface of the water. I realized the time for my death had come. The Lord drew me into himself by his breath. I lay dormant within him for many yugas. When the Lord contemplated creation once again, he gave me life by means of his senses. Thus you see me in the present form before you."

       Hearing the extraordinary story of Narada, do you not feel God had given him another life like any of us after a no rebirth assurance? His existence was not like the life human beings have. He had been given a life to serve for the benefit of all the three worlds. By the grace of God, the sage moved around unhindered, singing his greatness. This was his kainkarya, service to God, even though emancipated. With Narayana lodged in his heart, his songs were accompanied by the vibrating sound of the holy word OM, signifying the Supreme Truth of Brahman in a nutshell, emanating from his divine instrument Veena. Narada had risen to occupy the Paramapada, the final abode along with God.



 Sage Narada

       Now with a mind saturated with the thought of the Lord, Vyasa retired to the western banks of the holy river Sarasvati. He sat down concentrating on the Almighty God. The meditation helped him get a crystal clear knowledge of the real truth to distinguish the Lord from the illusory world. The maturity of his thinking prodded him to relieve the people from the miseries through his songs of the Bhagavatam.

   [In Telugu the word Bhagavatam is a five syllable word- 'Bhagavatamu' . Bha means bhakti (devotion); Ga is gyana (wisdom); Va stands for vairagyam(detachment); Ta for tatvam (absolute truth); Mu is mukti(emancipation).]

 </body>
</story>