<story>
<body>Chapter 27: Glories Galore

 

Blue berries: Krishna delighted the folks of Vraja by his pranks and endeared himself to one and all. Of and on he also gave a glimpse of his divinity by deeds beyond human capability. One day, he heard a woman selling blue berries. In response to her call, Krishna took a handful of rice to exchange it for her fruits. But before he reached her, the rice grains slowly dropped from his small hand, with only one grain left in his palm. The vendor woman, out of consideration for the child, gave him a handful of fruits in return for the grain of rice. The woman was astonished at the miracle that followed. Her basket was full to the brim with precious gems and jewels.
 
            After the incident of Trinavarta, the Vraja people were completely shaken, anticipating danger every moment. A senior gopa named Upananda suggested that all the inhabitants of Vraja moved to Brindavana, a safer place to live in. The omens did not seem favourable and it was unwise to continue in Vraja any longer. The general consensus was Brindavana would be an ideal option, having the welfare of the entire community in mind. The lush green pastures of the place would be congenial to them especially to the cattle of the cowherds. Krishna and Balarama jelled with the cowboys so well that they adopted their way of life. Accompanying them, they took the cattle for grazing in the meadows. The beauty of Brindavana, the mountain Govardhana and the banks of Yamuna fascinated them. All of them enjoyed playing various games together while tending the kine.
 
Vatsasura: It so happened that an asura sent by Kamsa, disguised as a calf [vatsa] was spotted by Krishna among the cattle. He discreetly informed his brother and they both casually walked into the herd. Krishna suddenly held the hind legs and the tail of the calf. He swirled it round a number of times with force and threw it into the air. The calf hit a kapittha fruit on a tree closeby. Both the calf and the fruit went hurling down. The impact of the fall smashed the demon to death. Krishnas victory over Vatsasura [asura as calf] was acclaimed by both the cowherds and the celestials. Another version of the story is that the kapittha fruit was also an asura and Krishna killed them both together.
 
            Vakasura: Next, it was Vakasura to fall into the hands of Krishna. One day, the cowherds led their cattle to a tank for water and they wanted to quench their thirst also. There they saw a ferocious looking crane [Vaka] sitting. The moment they reached the tank, the crane gulped Krishna whole. Balarama and the others stood paralysed, not knowing what to do. Krishna would not succumb to the threats of Kamsas emissaries of whom Vaka was one. Krishna began to scorch the throat of Vaka like fire which made him cough out the oppressor. Vaka did not let go Krishna. He tried to tear him with his beak but Krishna broke the beak as easily as snapping a twig.
 
            Aghasura: Expecting danger all the time, Kamsa had his mind fixed at finding an effective way to kill Krishna. He wanted to try his luck by sending Aghasura, the brother of Putana and Vakasura. Grieving over the death of his siblings, Aghasuras revengeful attitude was doubly stimulated. The cowherds were exhilarated during their play in the company of Krishna. The following and adoration Krishna enjoyed among his friends made his identity evident to Aghasura. To carry out the commands of Kamsa, he assumed the form of a serpent of enormous size with his mouth wide open extending from the earth to the sky. He placed himself at a vantage point in the vicinity of the cowherds. The serpent lay still with his mouth appearing like the entrance to a dark cave. The red tongue gave the impression of a pathway leading inside. Its sharp teeth were comparable to mountain peaks. The cowherds thought it to be part of natural enhancement of the scenic beauty of Brindavana, as they stood in admiration. The next moment they suspected that it could be a real serpent waiting to devour them. But it was only a passing thought. With Krishna by their side, they were confident that no harm could ever come to them. Boldly, they entered the deceptive serpent cave in a mood of adventurous exploration. The serpent was pleased to see the cowherds fallen into his trap and he was waiting for Krishna to follow suit. Krishna wanted to dissuade his friends but he was a little late to arrive at the spot. So he entered the snake cave and assumed an enormous body. He blocked the mouth completely which prevented even a draught of air from entering. The serpent was suffocated and his life became extinct with the vital air blowing out of his head. The cowherds escaped unharmed, resuscitated by the power of Krishna. When the five year old Krishna walked into the mouth of the snake, the deities were expecting a serious calamity but the way the young boy handled the situation delighted them with surprise. The dried skin of the snake later became the playground for the cowherd boys. Contrary to our expectation, the asura was emancipated by the Lord. The mere touch of Krishnas feet washed his sins and the Lords magnanimity pardoned him of his impiety.
 
Lords aim is to be good and merciful to all even if the merit is earned inadvertently. He has no grudge against anyone but guides all to reformation. That is the reason why Vishnu does not resort to curse as an expression of his dissatisfaction. Death penalty which is a punishment for repeated births is also for the incorrigible people alone. This exemplary attitude of the Lord is his Daya Bhava, his compassion.

Lord Venkatesvara
 
The famous saint philosopher Vedanta Desika has dedicated a hundred slokas in praise of this endearing quality in his Dayashatakam. He bows to the Tirupati Hill in the first verse which exquisitely brings out the power of the Lords Daya Bhava. What a wonderful metaphoric description of the beauty of the hill on which the Lord resides! Usually hills are made of stones and rocks but its not so with the sacred hill, says the poet. Presence of the Lord who has descended on earth as the idol of Venkateshvara on the seven hills has converted them into hills of crystalized sugar. Desika is visualizing the streams on the hills as the sugarcane juice flowing down by the Lords compassion. The image presented is the idea of the Lord residing on the solidified sugar hill created by his holy presence. His tender feelings are evoked by his devotees. The warmth of his compassion towards them melts the sugar that is the hill which often comes down in streams. The streams flowing from the hill have inspired the poet to metaphorically associate the hill and the flowing streams with sugar and sugarcane juice effected by Venkateshvara and his compassion respectively.
            
??????????? ?????? ?????: ?????????????????? |                
??????????????????? ??????????? ??????????? ||
 
Prapadyetam girim prayah shrinivasanukampaya
         Ikshusarasravantyeva yanmoortya sharkarayitam

             I bow to the hill, converted to crystalised sugar by the Lords presence as the idol, which often flows down as sugarcane juice by his compassion.
 
Dhenuka: Balarama and Krishna went to the forest with the cowboys and the cattle. One of the boys approached the brothers to tell them about the juicy fruits of the palm trees deep in the forest and expressed a desire to taste them. Balarama and Krishna, ever ready to please their friends, went to the palm trees and shook the trunks vigorously for the fruits. Asura Dhenuka was angry with the trespassers. He approached them in the form of an ass, furiously walking with a heavy gait. He assaulted Balarama, kicked him on the chest with his hind legs and forcibly pushed him to the ground. Taken unawares, Balarama could not offer any resistance. Dhenuka misjudged him to be a weakling and expected to overpower him easily by a similar second kick. But sadly, he made an ass of himself. He tried to attack once again but Balarama was alert this time. Holding his legs, he hit Dhenuka hard against the trunk of the palm tree with a vigorous swirl and killed him. Dhenukas relatives attacked them for the death of their kinsman but received the same treatment. Rohini and Yashoda performed benedictory rites to ward off evil as a result of their association with asuras. After that, the people entered the palm grove without fear and enjoyed the fruits for a long time.
 </body>
</story>