<story>
<body>Manu had two sons named Priyavrata and Uttanapada, both incarnations of Vishnu. Uttanapada had two wives, Suruchi and Suniti. Suruchi was dearer to him than his other wife. One day, Uttama was on his fathers lap when Uttanapada and Suruchi were seated on the throne. Sunitis son Dhruva, a child of five years, with a desire to sit on the lap along with his brother, tried to climb on to his father. Uttanapada made no attempts to help the small child to come on to his lap or show any affection by fondling him. Suruchi, the domineering wife, hurt the tender feelings of the child with harsh words. She said, Its a pity you are Sunitis son unlike Uttama who happens to be mine. You do not have the good fortune to sit on your fathers lap nor the right to the throne. If you wish to enjoy the privilege at least in your next birth, engage yourself in the meditation of the Supreme Lord. Go through severe austerities by which you may hope to be born as my son then. Uttanapada was a silent spectator without any reaction. Dhruva was terribly upset by his step-mothers heartless words. He ran to his mother crying inconsolably. She was also depressed on hearing about the incident from the attendants. With eyes filled with tears, she said, Just as your step-mother told you, my dear child, being my son you cannot aspire for the throne. Your father does not love me. I would advise you to emulate your illustrious grand-father. Strenuous penance and sincere service at Gods feet helped him finally attain emancipation after a prosperous life as a king.
 
Inspired by his mothers wise advice, he started towards the forest for practicing arduous penance. At that time, Narada came to dissuade the boy from venturing into such a rigorous task. He said, Dhruva, your age calls for a life of enjoyment and play, not for penance. Do not allow the words of wicked people to make any dent on your mind. At the same time let not the words of praise inflate your pride. The path you have chosen is not a bed of roses but a thorny one beyond your capacity to withstand. Go home, enjoy your childhood and come back when you are old enough for this kind of life. Dhruva thanked him for his concern but with humility conveyed to him that his mind was set on the goal. Impressed by his steadfast determination, Narada advised him to go to Madhuvana on the banks of Yamuna. He also taught Dhruva the nuances of penance to reach the Almighty. With due respect to the sage, Dhruva took leave to repair to the holy place.
 

                                                                 Dhruva meditates
 
On reaching his destination, he meticulously followed the instructions of Narada, with complete control over his mind and senses. He gradually increased the interval between the intake of food and finally he even gave up inhaling air so vital for existence. Standing motionless on one leg, withdrawn from the material world, Dhruva meditated on the Supreme Being. The gods were agitated with the high energy released by his penance and the earth too developed a depression by the pressure of his toe. With an intention to relieve the gods of their tension and in particular to express his delight over the small boys devotion, Lord Hari appeared before Dhruva. He told Dhruva that he would rule over his fathers kingdom for many kalpas and his life will finally culminate in the spiritual bliss. He also promised Dhruva a place of honour in the firmament as the brightest ever shining star. Dhruva became the Pole Star in the sky also known as the North Star.
 

Lord Hari appears before Dhruva
 
            Receiving the blessings, Dhruva started homewards to his fathers kingdom. Contemplating on his way back, he realized that he did not entertain any hatred towards his step-brother or step-mother. He was not angry over his fathers partiality. On the other hand he repented for his mental attitude when he walked out of the house. His only aim at that moment was to win the same degree of affection and attention from his father as his brother. He regretted aspiring for such a petty thing instead of Sri Haris blissful realm. He felt that in all probability, he was urged by jealousy, while immature age and mind eclipsed the wonders of attaining God. Endowed with a wider perspective of the value of life now, he grieved for his previous misplaced choice.
 
            In the kingdom, Uttanapada did not have peace of mind. May be, he was silent to Surichis rebuke out of fear for his cantankerous wife. In reality, he might have had no hatred for Dhruva, being Sunitis son, as Suruchi had made it appear. So he was suffering from a sense of guilt for being instrumental in the exile of his son. Though he was assured by Narada about Dhruvas outstanding future, he could not pardon his cruelty to his young child. To make amends for his past ill treatment, he proceeded to receive his son with honours. He placed him on an elephant for everyone to see the young boy who had won glories inconceivable at his age.
 
            Uttama was disinterested in ascending the throne. He was however killed by a yaksha in the forest. Dhruva was made the king. He was infuriated about his brothers death. Manu appeared before Dhruva to stop his inimical aggression towards the yakshas. He showed him the righteous way to deal with such situations. War was not the solution. Stooping low to retaliation influenced by emotion or sentiment was not worthy of a wise man. Equanimity should have command over ones frame of mind. Dhruva decided to turn a new leaf in his attitude in handling trying situations. He ruled successfully for many kalpas as advised by Manu. Then he retired to the forest in quest of spiritual emancipation.
 </body>
</story>