<story>
<body>Sarjati, Manus son took his daughter, Sukanya, to the hermitage of Chyavana muni. She unknowingly poked a thorn into something luminous in an ant-hill. They looked like a pair of glow worms but were actually the eyes of the muni inside. Excessive bleeding from the ant-hill, made Sarjati tremble terribly with fear. Sukanya readily took responsibility for the folly and Sarjatis efforts pacified the muni as soon as he came out of the ant-hill. He was an old man with wrinkled skin and emaciated body. He expressed his desire to marry Sukanya. Sarjati agreed and the marriage was performed. Sukanya served her aged husband devotedly.
 
 
Chyavana and Sukanya
           
            Once, the muni got an opportunity to serve faithfully the twin celestial physicians, the Ashvini Kumaras. He told them, You two are the competent physicians of the gods. You alone can bestow youth on me. I request you to bless me with an attractive figure. In return, I will secure the soma juice, offered during sacrifices, denied to you till now." The twins accepted the offer and asked the muni to take a dip in the nearby river along with them. When they emerged from the water, three identical youths appeared before Sukanya, confusing her to pick her husband from among them. She sought the help of the Ashvini Kumaras, who were happy with her fidelity to her husband and pointed the actual muni to her.
 
            Sometime later, Sarjati wanted muni Chyavana to officiate as the chief priest for a big sacrifice he intended to perform. He visited the hermitage to extend a personal invitation to the sage. He was shocked to see his daughter living with a handsome youth. He was furious with his daughter. He shouted at her, You have defamed our family as well as that of the respectful sage. How could you live with another man when you had such a distinguished sage for a husband? You unchaste woman, I am ashamed to own you, of condemnable character, as my daughter. Sukanya clarified the mistaken impression of her father. She explained in detail the way her husband had attained youth. It was nectar to his ears and happily he invited the muni to receive the high honour at his sacrifice. The muni accepted the invitation and successfully completed the sacrifice. In accordance with his promise, he offered soma juice to the Ashvini Kumaras and incorporated them among those eligible for that privilege. Indra furiously aimed his thunder bolt at the muni for going against the convention. The muni by his yogic powers arrested the weapon. Finally the gods agreed to include the twins and ever since, they have been enjoying the soma juice offered during sacrifices.
 

Interesting Anecdotes

           

            Sukanya and Chyavana: The story of Sukanya and Chyavana has another narration too. Once, Sukanya was bathing in the river, when the Ashvini Kumaras approached her. They said, What a monotonous life you are leading with that old rishi Chyavana who needs your attention all day long. You have no time for yourself to enjoy. Your beauty deserves a better life, one full of enjoyment, free from the drudgery you have undertaken. You are young and so are we. You can forsake that living corpse and choose one of us bubbling with youth. We will be a perfect match for you. The devoted wife was upset with the Ashvini Kumaras and said she would like to consult her husband. She soon returned with the rishi. On seeing the rishi, the two deities suggested, the rishi can take a dip in the river along with us. When we come out, the three of us will be identical youths. You can then choose your husband from among us. If there is any difficulty in selection, you can use your mental faculty to discern. Sukanya agreed to their suggestion because she was very confident about herself and was courageous to take up the challenge. When the three young men emerged from the water, Sukanya had no problem identifying her own husband. The Ashvini Kumaras as well as Chyavana were very pleased with Sukanya for her fidelity.
 
            It was actually a test for Sukanyas faithful devotion to her aged husband. It had to be ascertained whether she was really dedicated to her husband or was she biding time as atonement for her folly as a young girl (when she unknowingly poked the rishis eyes in the ant-hill), waiting for the first opportunity to elope with a handsome youth. When she succeeded, she proved that  she did not treat her marriage as a temporary agreement. It was not  just to appease the anger of the rishi when he came out of the ant-hill with bleeding eyes. She had treated her marriage as a solemn oath. Chyavana was grateful to the celestial physicians for bestowing youth on him. For Sukanya too, it was an unexpected jack pot prize for her earnestness to her husband all these years, even though he was emaciated with old age. In return, the rishi secured for the divine twins the soma juice, offered in the sacrifices, which was denied to them till then.
             Intelligent Ashvini Kumaras: The celestial physicians requested the great sage Dadheechi to teach them the sacred Truth about Brahman. The sage was well versed in Brahmagyana and he was Indras preceptor on this subject. Indra threatened the sage that he would lose his head if he revealed the secret knowledge to the twin deities. The shrewd gods were not to be cowed down by Indra. Since they were determined to acquire the sacred knowledge, they planned a device to save the life of the sage even if his head was chopped off by Indra. They removed the head of the rishi and placed a horses head in its place. Then they received the initiation on Brahman from Dadheechi. Furious Indra could not accept the transgression of his command and promptly cut off the sages head. The Ashvini Kumaras replaced the original head and thus revived Dadheechi. It is for this reason the rishi is called Ashvashira.

 </body>
</story>