<story>
<body>Chapter 43: Narakasura encounter

            The rivalry of the asuras and the deities was so strong and bitter that there was a constant battle between the two. Quite a few times, the deities were defeated and Indra dethroned. The added humiliation was that once Narakasura stole Indras umbrella and his mother Aditis ear-rings. What was more cruel was that Narakasura had locked up many women in his kingdom. As always, Krishna represented the deities to oppose the asuras. Krishna mounted his vehicle Garuda with Satyabhama by his side and landed in the city of Prajyotsana.
 
            This city of asura Mura was guarded by forests, mountain and other impenetrable, misleading devices as in a maze. The combined power of the Lords mace and discus razed the fortress to the ground. Asura Mura, who was sleeping under water, was awakened by the loud sound from the conch Panchajanya of Krishna. The five headed asura attacked with the three pronged shaft and his mace flew with great velocity towards Garuda. Krishna successfully arrested all of them and his sudarshana chakra finally killed the asura. The seven sons of Mura were enraged at the death of their father. Advised by Naraka to continue the fight, they entered the battlefield led by their commander-in-chief Pitha. Krishna proved too strong for the seven sons and they fell like nine pins. Naraka noticed that the army was incapable of any resistance against Krishna. He decided to accept the challenge himself. The two divine powers, Krishna and Garuda, wiped out the entire army without trace. Naraka now found himself standing alone in the combat. His powerful weapons like shakti and shataghni did not work against either Garuda or Krishna. Naraka fell to Sri Haris [Krishnas] discus.                                                         
 
            Bhoomi, mother of Naraka, appeared before the Lord. She sang his praises and returned Aditis ear-rings and Indras umbrella. She bowed and apologized for the sins of her son. She requested the gracious Lord to show mercy by placing his hands on her sons head. The lifeless body of Naraka that lay at Krishnas feet was symbolic of his surrender, she said. Granting her requests, Krishna entered the prosperous city of Naraka. There he found Naraka had under his custody ten thousand and hundred celestial women. Handsome Krishna captivated their hearts and they wanted him to accept all of them as his wives.
 
            Krishna took those women clad in fine clothes in palanquins to Dvaraka. Going to Indrapuri, he handed over Aditis jewels and Indras umbrella. Satyabhama wished to have the celestial Parijata tree. Indra refused to permit Krishna to uproot it. Indra wanted Krishnas help when he was in trouble but now having achieved his objective, he was prepared to stand up against his saviour for a Parijata tree. No need to say who the victor was. Krishna brought the tree and planted it in Satyabhamas garden which attracted bees even from the celestial regions.
 

Krishna uproots Parijata tree
 
The women, who had been offered asylum in Krishnas palace, were ever ready to serve him though there were attendants to take care of his needs. Krishna also reciprocated their love by assuming as many forms as the number of women and pleased them simultaneously.
 

Narakasura women get asylum
 </body>
</story>