<story>
<body>Gadhi was born to Kushambi, of the Puru dynasty. He had a beautiful daughter Satyavati. A brahmana by the name Richika, conveyed to Gadhi of his wish to marry his daughter. Gadhi was not in favour of the alliance and at the same time did not want to give a negative reply to the brahmana. He thought out a plan, which he believed would save him from embarrassment. He demanded a dowry which ordinarily would be impossible to give. Gadhi wanted one thousand horses effulgent like the moon with a dark blue ear on one side. Richika saw through the trick and straight away went to Varuna for help. He readily supplied the required number of horses satisfying the description. Gadhi was completely floored by the unexpected dowry from the brahmana. Satyavati married Richika.
 
            Satyavati and her mother desired to have sons. Therefore the Muni prepared separately two pots of sweet charu. He consecrated one with brahmana mantra for his wife and the other with kshatra mantra for his mother-in-law. When he had gone away for his ablution, the mother wanted the charu pots to be interchanged. She strongly felt that the charu meant for her daughter was superior to the one for her. Unsuspecting Satyavati agreed to the switching of the pots and both consumed the charu in the absence of the muni.
 
            When the muni returned, he came to know of the swapping of charu. The muni informed his wife the tragic consequence of the interchange. He said, Your action will result in your bearing a son who will be a cruel chastiser of his foes. Your brother will be a pious man devoted to the worship of the Supreme Lord. Shocked by the revelation, Satyavati implored that such a thing should not happen. The mistake could not be fully rectified, but the muni made a marginal concession. She would have to accept her grandson to have that terrible quality.
 

 Parashurama
           
            Soon Satyavati had Jamadagni as her son. His youngest son was Parashurama who vanquished the wicked kshatriyas twenty one times from the face of the earth. The elimination of these perpetrators of unethical and immoral actions was a great relief for mother earth. The severe reaction of Parashurama towards the kshatriyas stimulates our curiosity to investigate into the cause of such enmity.
 
 Kartaveeryarjuna, a kshatriya king, served Dattatreya, the form of Lord Hari on earth. His sincere service earned for him extraordinary prowess and wealth. He possessed one thousand arms. With the arrogance of power, he speeded round the earth like whirlwind. He reversed the flow of river Narmada with his innumerable arms. This flooded the banks on which the ten-headed Ravana was camping with his army. Infuriated by the inconvenience caused, the demon waged war against Kartaveeryarjuna who captured and imprisoned the aggressor in his capital Maheshmatipuri. Later he released him, finding the rival to be worthless.
    
            Parashurama was away from the hermitage of Jamadagni, when Kartaveeryarjuna came there during one of his expeditions. Jamadagni thought him to be a god among men, and extended due hospitality to Kartaveeryarjuna with his entire paraphernalia following him. The sages sacred cow provided all the articles to entertain the honoured guest. The wicked king exhibited his ungrateful nature by setting his eyes on the wish-yielding cow as he saw inexhaustible wealth in her. He ordered his men to bind the cow and take her to his kingdom. The pathetic cry of the cow did not arouse any pity in the king, bereft as he was of tender feelings.
 

 Jamadagni's cow stolen
          
            Soon Parashurama returned and stood aghast at the kings evil intentions. He picked up his terrible axe, charging like a furious bull at Kartaveeryarjuna. Observing Parashurama set for an indomitable attack, the king sent a large army to repulse him. The soldiers were no match to the powerful Parashurama who snuffed out their lives single handed. The valour of Parashurama made Kartaveeryarjuna take to his heels and the chase looked like a lion after its prey. Kartaveeryarjunas arms were lopped off by the axe and so was his head. His fallen body without the head resembled the stump of a tree. Kartaveeryarjunas death at the hands of Parashurama brought to an end his treachorous sovereignty that rocked the entire world. Parashurama presented the cow to his father, with a sense of achievement. But Jamadagnis reaction dampened his excitement. He said, My glorious son! Killing a consecrated king is more heinous than that of a brahmana. You are a brahmana whose primary and powerful quality should be forbearance, a quality that earns us veneration. Brahma too got universal acclaim through forbearance. As atonement for your sin, undertake a pilgrimage to concentrate on Sri Hari. Parashurama went on a years pilgrimage on his fathers advice.
 
            On his return, the purity and strength of his conscience was put to test. The big challenge was to choose between his father and his mother with his brothers. His mother had gone to the river to bring water for the performance of her husbands daily religious rites. She tarried a while admiring the handsome king Chitraratha of the gandharvas, sporting with the apsaras in the water. A moments lapse in the control of her mind earned her the disrepute of infidelity when her husband outright decried her as unchaste. He tried to order each of his sons to kill the mother as punishment. They refused to kill their mother and also a woman to whom they owed their very existence. Parashurama, a shrewd man, knew the veracity of his fathers spiritual power. To avert a sure disaster if not agreed upon, he consented to carry out his fathers command. Jamadagni was mightily pleased with his son and offered him a boon. Grabbing the opportunity, he pleaded for the resuscitation of his mother and brothers with the request that they should not have the slightest memory of their death or what had happened prior to that. Caught unawares by the intelligence of his son, he granted the boon. Parashurama proved to be a dutiful son in carrying out his obligation to both his parents.
 
The aggrieved sons of Kartaveeryarjuna were spoiling for a fight to avenge their fathers death. They entered the hermitage of Jamadagni in the absence of his sons,charged at the pious man to cut off his head.Despite his wife Renukas pleadings, they did not spare her husband and carried away the head. She started crying loudly calling for Parashurama. The lamenting mothers voice hastened him back to the hermitage. Learning about his father's killing, Parashurama proceeded to Maheshmatipuri. His axed down all the sons of Kartaveeryarjuna, piled them in a heap and allowed their blood to flow as a river. He indulged in this horrendous act to warn people to stay away from enmity towards brahmanas. With a vengence he vanquished the entire kshatriya class twenty one times to mark the number his mother had beat her chest at the murder of her husband. Nine rivers of blood flowed out of the sacred place Samanta-panchaka.
 

Parashurama's vengence
 
Parashurama brought his fathers head and attached it to his body by which he was revived. Jamadagni became the seventh saint in the constellation of seven saints. Parashurama was advised by his ancestors to desist forever from such inhuman massacre when he lost to Bhishma. He propitiated Lord Narayana by a sacrifice, followed by liberal gifts to brahmanas and finally had a dip in the river Sarasvati to expiate his sins. In the next creation, Parashurama promulgated the Vedas and is believed to be still living in Mount Mahendra.
 

 

Interesting Anecdotes

Vishvamitra: Gadhi had a very powerful son named Vishvamitra. His steadfast practice of asceticism to become a rishi, though belonging to the royal family, elevated him to the status of a raja rishi. He had many sons of his own but he adopted Shunashepa, the son of Ajigarta of the Bhrigu race. He named him Devarata and considered him as his first son. He wanted his own sons to treat him as their elder brother. Though they entertained resentment, the fear of their fathers curse made them agree to the suggestion. It is believed that the adoption of Devarata is the cause for various subdivisions of the Kaushika race of Vishvamitra.</body>
</story>