<story>
<body>One day, Parikshit was out hunting all alone. He was thirsty after a hot chase of a herd of deer. Going a long way in search of water, he located the hermitage of a pious sage named Shamika. The sage was in deep meditation, resigned from his worldly surrounding and in communion with God. The sage seated on a deer skin with knotted disheveled hair, was in a sublime state of mind. The arrival of the king went unnoticed and his request for water also did not draw the attention of the muni. The king with parched throat and suffering from near dehydration mistook the sages silence as indifference. Hospitality is the foremost etiquette expected towards the king. Absence of it was misconstrued by Parikshit as gross insult. Severe thirst had robbed the kings good sense. He developed a suspicion as to whether the sage was genuinely in meditation or was it a pretense to spite him. In a fit of anger, he picked up a dead snake lying at the doorstep with the tip of the bow and threw it round the neck of the muni. Then he proceeded homeward in a fury.
 

Parikshit throws a snake on the sage
           
            The sages son Shringi heard from his friends how his father had been treated by the king. Feeling very sorry for his father, the young boy, in an emotional outburst, cursed the king that he would die within seven days, bitten by the serpent takshaka. Crying aloud, the boy came to the hermitage when his father had just come out of meditation. On being informed about the curse on the king, Shamika was extremely depressed over his sons impulsive action. He then explained to Shringi the gravity of his mistake. He said, A devout follower of Sri Hari has been punished by you. Impropriety is unknown in his kingdom. Since a brahmanas curse cannot be reversed, I dread to think of the calamity that would occur after the kings death. Degeneration of society would be a sure consequence with the decline of virtue.
           

                                                                   Parikshit cursed</body>
</story>