<story>
<body>Lord decides to come down to earth either at the end of a kalpa marked by the occurrence of deluge to save the lives on earth or to set righteousness back on its rails.
 
            The end of a kalpa of the universe constitutes also the end of Brahmas day. Once on such an occasion, having reached the end of his day, Brahma retired to rest and out of force of habit he recited the Vedas in his sleep. Hayagriva, a danava with a horse head, sitting close to him, stole the Vedas by sheer power of concentration. Perceiving the action of Hayagriva, Sri Hari retrieved the Vedas from him and also saved the living species from deluge that followed by assuming the form of a fish.
 
            In the kalpa preceding the above mentioned deluge, there was a king named Satyavrata, of the Dravida territory. He was a great devotee of Lord Narayana, given to severe austerities and subsisting only on water. Satyavrata was born as the grandson of Aditi and Kashyapa, through Vivasvan, the sun god.
 
            One day, standing in the river Kritamala, Satyavrata was offering a handful of water to the manes. He found a small fish along with the water in the hollow of his palms. Inadvertently he dropped the fish back in to the river. The fish pleaded the exalted soul to save it from the dangerous aquatic creatures that survive on the weaker ones. Out of pity, Satyavrata brought it with him in his kamandalu. Soon the fish had to be transferred to a pitcher as it had outgrown the size of the kamandalu. With the rapid growth of the fish, it had to be taken from one pond to another, each larger than the previous one. Finding no suitable place to accommodate the gigantic fish, the raja rishi decided to let it into the ocean. The fish expressed its fear of the alligators and requested him to be very vigilant about its safety. The enormous size assumed by the fish just in the course of the day, convinced Satyavrata beyond doubt that it was none other than Lord Hari himself. He then enquired the fish about the purpose of taking such a form.
 
            The fish informed him of the approaching deluge and that it had come as an incarnation of the Lord, the saviour of his devotees. It expected the king to cooperate by following its instruction strictly. The fish said, In a weeks time, the earth, heaven and the aerial region will all be submerged in the rising water of the ocean leading to the dissolution of the universe. Before that happens, you will have to take certain precautionary measures. Collect the various seeds, plants, all living species, along with seven seers and await the arrival of the boat sent by the Lord. Load it with the material you would have already collected. Navigate the boat unnerved in the surging water, with the guidance of the seers. I will appear as a fish with a horn. The serpent Vasuki should be used as rope to tie the boat to my horn. I will keep the boat afloat till Brahma wakes from his slumber. At that time, you will have a glorious experience of visualizing the Parabrahman [the Transcendental Reality] residing within your heart. The knowledge of Reality imparted by the Lord himself will clear all your doubts and satiate the curiosity about the Supreme Being. The fish disappeared at the conclusion of its instructions to the king.
 
             Settling down to his meditation of the Lord in the form of the fish, with the things diligently brought together as directed, Satyavrata eagerly looked forward to the boat. Soon he sighted it. He boarded the boat with the seers and all the things to be preserved for the future. The rishis asked Satyavrata to concentrate on the Lord who would rescue them. The king meditated accordingly. In response, the Lord instantly arrived as the huge horned fish. The king tied the boat to the horn of the fish with Vasuki. He began singing the glories of Vishnu, who emancipates the devotees in his domain called Paramapada, a place from where there is no return to birth or death. Praying to the Lord cleanses the impurities of ignorance, enlightens the mind to shed the destructive ego and prepares one to see the indwelling Parabrahman. Pleased with the royal sage, Lord Vishnu educated him on the Sankhya Philosophy which is available to us as the divine purana called the Matsyapurana. In the incarnation of the Lord as the fish, he killed the demon Hayagriva. He retrieved the Vedas just before the deluge and handed them back to Brahma in the shvetavaraha kalpa that followed the kalpa of Satyavrata.Vaivasvata Manu was also known by the name Shraddhadeva.
 </body>
</story>