<story>
<body>Chapter 36: Education of the Brothers

 

The reverential attitude of Vasudeva and Devaki did not please Balarama or Krishna. They wanted to be like other ordinary sons to their parents. To establish their natural relationship, Krishna spoke to his parents thus, We are exceedingly happy to be united with you, our dear parents. Due to circumstances beyond our control, we were not fortunate to be under your protection. Not only that. We have made you go through great difficulties. Now that the major evil in the form of Kamsa is no more, we would like to keep you happy and in peace. Permit us to look after your welfare as well as protect the young children, aged people and the downtrodden among us. That would give us an opportunity to conduct ourselves as dutiful sons. With his maya, Krishna was able to make his parents behave with them as normal parents. They could now see them as sons and not as the form of God Vishnu. Vasudeva and Devaki embraced their sons affectionately and it was at last a happy union of the family.
 
Next, Krishna placed his revered grandfather on the throne as the sovereign monarch. Knowing the desire of his grandfather to crown him as the king, Krishna diplomatically refused giving the excuse of a past curse which denied the Yadus to kingship. Krishna also thought that the kingdom belonged to his grandfather. So it was legitimate that he be honoured. He enjoyed the pleasure of standing in attendance on his grandfather which, in turn, gave the utmost happiness to the old king. He was emotionally moved by Krishnas affection for he had not received so much respect or love from his own son.
 
The king advised his daughter and son-in-law to make arrangement for the investiture of the sacred thread, as the two boys had reached the eligible age. His words were respected and the boys formally took to Brahmacharya. After the successful completion of the thread ceremony, they expressed a desire to be initiated by a guru in the traditional way of gurukulavasa, studying under a preceptor residing in his hermitage. They were entrusted to sage Sandipani and his able tutelage. Both of them were quick to grasp the instructions of the preceptor and comprehended the Vedas as well as the other sciences of philosophy and logic. At the completion of their education, they wished that their gurudakshina, offered as a mark of gratitude, should be most appreciated by their guru. Sage Sandipini replied with pleasure, I did not have to exert to tutor you. I am honoured to have had such precocious pupils who needed just a suggestive hint to comprehend the subject in its entirety. My mental gratification at your intellectual excellence is as good as gurudakshina. If you are insistent, I would like you to retrieve my infant son who was accidentally swallowed by the ocean near the temple Pravasa.
 
Balarama and Krishna waited on the sands of the ocean for quite some time. The lord of the ocean came out with gifts and offered his services to them. When Krishna asked for the return of his gurus infant son whom he took away accidentally, the ocean lord pleaded innocence. He said that the child could have been kidnapped by the asura Panchajana living in the water as a conch. Krishna jumped into the water and killed the asura but the child was not to be found in his belly. Krishna came out of the ocean with the conch Panchajanya that emerged from the asuras body.
 

Right spiral and left spiral
 
[Panchajanya means having control over the five classes of beings.The conch is considered as an emblem of power, sovereignty and authority. The sound of the conch is believed to ward off evil spirits and natural calamities. It is also a war trumpet and every powerful warrior owned his conch with an individual name. Krishna's conch was Panchajanya and Arjuna's was called Devadatta.
There is a natural fundamental difference in the structure of formation of conches. One spirals to the right in the clockwise direction while the other has the left spiral. The former is very rare and sacred. The sound from this kind of conch is accepted as the echo of the celestial motion of the sun, moon, planets and stars across the heavens. Krishna's Panchajanya was right spiralled. The loud blowing sound of the conch is called shankha ghosha or just ghosha, shankha-rava or shankha-svana.] 
 
Krishna felt that Yama might be having the child. He went to the kingdom of death and blew the conch Panchajanya calling the king to the doorstep. Krishna asked him to return his gurus son and Yama obediently brought the child alive to the Lord. The child was handed over to the guru by Krishna and Balarama. The guru was very thankful to them for the most invaluable gurudakshina he had ever received.
 

Yama summoned to deliver guru's child</body>
</story>