<story>
<body>Chapter 31: Rasa Leela

 


Rasaleela

 Rasa Leela is a dramatic presentation of the gopis complete dedication to God. These verses in the Bhagavatam, extol the Sharanagathi [complete self surrender to God] of the Bhagavad Gita in the form of a simple dance drama.
In the Bhagavad Gita, the Lord says:
 
???? ??????? ?????????? ??????? ????? ???? |
???? ???? ???? ???????? ????????????? ?? ???: ||
 
Sarva dharman parityajya mamekam sharanam vraja
Aham tva sarva papebhyo mokshayishyami ma shucha:
           
Surrender unto me giving up all discriminations of caste or creed. I shall emancipate you from your sins, have no doubt about that. 
 
            Yet another interpretation of this verse:
            Give up all other methods of seeking the Paramapada, like Jnanamarga, karmamarga or bhaktimarga as they will lead to only the lower worlds like heaven and such others. Not that these will not lead to emancipation. But they are difficult methods which great munis alone can follow successfully. These are definitely beyond the capability of common man. It requires high degree of discipline, not every person can pursue in a sustained manner. Moreover they are gradual, taking step by step to various higher worlds. While enjoying the second grade happiness in these worlds, man will roll back, with the exhaustion of the merits that took him to the impermanent small elevation. Instead, sharanagati is the simplest way to reach God. When a devotee falls at the feet of the Lord with utmost faith, nothing more is expected of him. God will take over the responsibility to deliver him from all his sins.  When there is relief from sins, the royal gate of Paramapada open for him. That's the assurance the Lord gives.
           
            In the life of human beings, the relationship between the husband and wife is the closest, pure and most abiding. That is why, the Bhagavatam depicts the Katyayani vow observed by the gopis, as a prayer to have Krishna as their husband, not out of lust but for the long cherished everlasting intimacy with God. Is it not surprising to find that the gopas did not suspect the fidelity of their wives when they spent a whole night dancing with Krishna? Moreover, their response to the melodies of Krishnas flute, in preference to their household responsibilities, was also not taken amiss. The reason being, they were mentally mature to know the nature of God. God dwells within everybody and service to God is service to all. God treats his devotees with parity without any emtoional involvement. The purity of devotion of the gopis and Krishnas reciprocal gratification were evident to the gopas. 
 
            Rasa Leela was Krishnas gift to the gopis for their ardent devotion to him. Therefore, though it was an autumn night when the surroundings were barren and dry, he created an illusion of the beauty of spring season, a season that inspires love and congenial to have a merry dance. The sweet sound from his flute was the divine call which drew the gopis towards him. Instantly dropping the activities they were engaged in, they began walking in a daze, as if, hypnotized by the melodious music. With Krishna as the central figure and the gopis dancing round him, Krishnas Rasa Leela took off to a wonderful start. Krishna obliged by taking as many forms as the gopis and danced in partnership with each one of them. In the frenzy over the extraordinary experience, every gopi imagined herself lucky with a little pride, to be the chosen favourite of the Lord. Krishna thought, he should curb the egoism slowly taking root in the gopis. It is an unhealthy trait to encourage, as it is aroused by the misconception of the Lords attitude towards his devotees. At the same time, the Lord wanted to instill humility to show that it was the most important quality to reach the feet of God. Krishna decided to disappear from their midst. The gopis were disappointed to find the Lord suddenly out of sight. They wondered why he had left them abruptly without any reason. They were depressed to find that their luck to enjoy the divine company was so short lived. Yet as if possessed, they continued dancing in a world of their own, impersonating one another for Krishna. Each ones pride over receiving exclusive favour of the Lord vanished with the shock treatment, as it were, given by Krishna. Seeing the steadfast devotion of the simple women, Krishna took pity for subjecting them to the litmus test. He again presented himself before them offering divine bliss in bountiful. They danced with Krishna till the wee hours of the morning and then reluctantly turned their footsteps homewards. Krishna brings home to all of us by his Rasa Leela that one can obtain the benevolence of God only by humble attitude of complete surrender which must be cultivated within ones mind and heart.
 

Reunion of gopis with Krishna
 </body>
</story>