<story>
<body>Chapter 46: Beloved Sudama

            Childhood friendship is quite often forgotten when individual careers lead to different roads. Friends also fall out when one becomes prosperous and the other writhes in poverty. But the friendship of Krishna and Sudama that blossomed during their stay in the gurukula, never faded, even though Krishna had become a king and Sudama was struggling for one meagre meal.
 
            Sudama was a Brahmana, married to a devoted woman who ungrudgingly accepted his poverty. Sudama never went seeking for food but was satisfied with whatever came voluntarily from people. Insufficient food reduced them to a skeleton and their clothes were in tatters that barely covered them. Yet they led a peaceful happy life.
 
            One day, the pangs of hunger were so severe that the wife was on the verge of collapse. She was reminded of Krishna, known for his generosity and who was also Sudamas dear friend. She approached her husband and said, O lord! Hunger has driven me to a state of faint. So much is spoken about the large heartedness of your childhood friend, Krishna, the king of Dvaraka. For old acquaintance sake, he will surely be charitable to you and do something about our dire poverty. Sudama welcomed the suggestion not for the prospect of getting monetary assistance but for the opportunity of meeting his childhood friend, the Universal Lord. He enthusiastically started on his journey to Dvaraka. Though he did not have any present worth the name, he carried with him four handfuls of beaten rice in a small bundle, the only thing his wife could offer as a humble gift.
 

 Krishna honours Sudama
          
            Sudama was admitted into the portals of Krishnas palace. Krishna was excited to meet his old friend and went forward to welcome him. His affectionate embrace revealed his immense happiness. Krishna honoured Sudama by seating him on the bed and washing his feet. The women in the household attended on him with respect and saw to it that he was comfortable and at ease. Sudama was exhilarated to see Krishnas humility even as a king and the bond of friendship between them still holding strong. The relish with which Krishna ate the poor mans beaten rice made Sudama feel that henceforth poverty had no meaning in his life. The very sight of Krishna had alleviated his misery and his wifes advice to him evaporated into thin air. His contentment was so satisfying that he could not care to ask him for help. He thought money had no value after he had seen Krishna so unassuming and simple in his approach to life.
 
            After an unforgettable stay at Dvaraka, Sudama took leave to go back home. Throughout the return journey, he was thinking how to give a picturesque description to his wife about his wonderful stay with Krishna. He knew the nature of his wife. Seeing him back with only a heart full of delightful contentment, his good wife would not entertain any grouse against him. Being an understanding wife, he knew she would excuse him for avoiding the mention of their poverty to Krishna and let go a golden chance of seeing better days. She would surely not rub in her frustration endlessly and make their happy life a misery. Thus, confident of his wifes reaction, he reached home floating in the pleasant memory of the best days of his life. To his utter astonishment, he found a large beautiful castle in the place where his dilapidated hut had previously stood for years. A chariot, horses and cattle could be seen in their sheds outside the house and men came hurrying to attend on him. For a moment, all this unexpected prosperity seemed very unreal, creating a doubt as to whether he was at the wrong place. He had not come out of the bewilderment, when his wife walked out of the palatial house, gorgeously dressed with fineries and maids following close behind. She greeted him with a broad smile and happily expressed her gratitude to Sudama for agreeing to approach his generous friend. Sudama stood speechless but he mentally went back to Krishna to convey his heartfelt gratitude for all that the Lord had done for him. Aware of Sudamas sincere devotion, the Lord had bestowed his benevolent grace unobtrusively.
 

Krishna gifts Sudama a castle
 
            Sudama lived the rest of his life with his wife in luxury though never enamoured by the worldly attractions. He had given himself to meditation of the Lord and in due course reached the feet of God in Paramapada.</body>
</story>