<story>
<body>Chapter 24: Kamsa hears a divine voice

 

Warmongering asuras were a menace on earth assuming forms of arrogant kings assisted by their armies. The celestials too found it difficult to endure their atrocities. They approached Brahma in the form of a wailing cow. With tears rolling down her eyes, she sought redressal for her distress. Brahma, Shiva and other deities went to the milky ocean. Brahma meditated on the Supreme Being by reciting the Purushasukta, the sacred hymn of the Rigveda. Brahma heard a voice from the heavens, as he was meditating. The voice gave clear instructions for the deities to act upon. Brahma carefully grasped what he heard and guided the deities accordingly. The gods were to be born as Yadavas and the Lord himself would be the son of Vasudeva. Ananthashesha, his constant companion, would precede him as his elder brother to carry out the favourite biddings of the Lord. The Lords illusory energy will descend as Yoga-maya to suitably organise the situations for the Lords mission on earth.
 
            As the curtain rises to present the Lords plan, it unfurls the story of the birth and life of Sri Krishna, the son of Vasudeva. Vasudeva, the descendent of the Surasena dynasty, married Devaki, the princess of Mathura, daughter of king Ugrasena. Kamsa was Devakis brother. He enthusiastically hoisted himself as the charioteer to please his sister, who was leaving for her husbands home, the city of Surasena. His excitement as he drove the chariot was dampened by a voice from heaven. It warned him that his death would be brought about by the eighth son of Devaki. Shocked by what he heard, Kamsa at once drew his sword to kill Devaki. He thought he could falsify the prophecy by the death of his sister which would throttle the birth of even one son to her.
 

 Kamsa hears divine voice
           
            Vasudeva tried to pacify Kamsa with conciliatory words. He said, Only evil minded people ought to be scared of death. As the protector of your subjects, you have been a successful and a fair king. For what reason then would the son of Devaki want to kill a noble king? Devaki, who is like a daughter to you, should not be killed when her marriage festivities are not yet over. As if possessed by a devil, he was not in a state of mind to take any kind of advice. Only the act of killing was dominating his thought at that point of time. His brain was paralysed with the threat of death looming over his head. Vasudeva, in a desperate attempt to appease Kamsa, finally offered him each of his sons as soon as they were born, if his wife was spared. Kamsa had faith in Vasudeva and was convinced that he would not go back on his words. So he decided against the impelling urge to kill Devaki. Vasudeva kept his promise which mightily pleased Kamsa. In a chivalrous mood, Kamsa returned to Vasudeva, the first child, as only the eighth son was to ring his death knell. The other sons were insignificant to him. Vasudeva was very happy to take back the child but at the same time he was skeptical about Kamsas generosity.   
 
            At that time, Narada came to apprise Kamsa about the people of Vraja, Yadus and Vrishnis. The sage told him that the Yadavas represented the celestials descended to vanquish the asuras increasingly becoming a burden to the earth. Terribly shaken by the warning, Kamsa began to see the form of Vishnu in every child of Devaki. He imprisoned Vasudeva and Devaki, binding them with chains. He went back to his original agreement with Vasudeva and killed his sons as soon as they were born. His disposition towards the Yadus was bitter as the eighth son of Devaki would also be a Yadu, a cowherd community, to which Vasudeva belonged. Kamsa put in prison his own father, Ugrasena, as he was sympathetic towards his daughter and son-in-law. Having removed all dangerous obstacles, Kamsa assumed the lordship of Surasena and began to enforce his authoritarian rule.
 
            The entire force of the asura kings allied with Kamsa to harass the Yadus jointly. The Yadus found it unbearable and scattered to other surrounding states. The first six sons of Devaki met their end by the barbarity of Kamsa. The seventh child in Devakis womb was Ananthashesha. The Lord began to organise things well in advance, even before Kamsa had an indication about the arrival of the seventh child. The Lord deputed the goddess of illusory energy, Yoga-maya to transfer the foetus into the womb of Rohini, another wife of Vasudeva, hiding in the mountain cave of the region under the rule of cowherd Nanda. This child would be known as Sankarshana, for being moved from one womb to another. He would also be known as Rama for the delight he would give to everyone. Balabhadra would be another name, popularly known as Balarama, in appreciation of his prowess. When the foetus was removed from Devakis womb, people thought she had lost her child prematurely. How can people understand the divine manipulation which is beyond human comprehension? Saving the seventh son thus, God had to make arrangements to deceive Kamsa, when the Lord himself would incarnate as the eighth child of Devaki. He moved on to his next miracle.
 
             With the conception of the eighth child of Devaki, Yashoda, Nandas wife, conceived Yoga-maya as her daughter. Honoured by people, the esteemed daughter of Yashoda would have various temples erected, with her as the presiding deity. She would be known by various names as Durga, Vijaya, Vaishnavi, Badrakali, Kumuda, Chandrika, Krishna, Madhavi, Kanyaka, Maya, Narayani, Ishani, Sharada and Ambika. The Lord at the same time revealed himself to Devaki and Vasudeva. Devakis unusual hallowed glow instilled fear in Kamsa who suspected that the Lord was already on his way to appear on earth. He desisted from his temptation to kill Devaki because he realised that homicide was the most deplorable act one could stoop down to. He was convinced it was the sure way to invite irrevocable misery, not only to oneself but to future generations as well. It would also throw the sinful into the cauldron in hell. Consumed by fear, Kamsa began to visualize the Lord all round in the entire universe.
 

 Krishna is born
           
            While Kamsas disturbed mind was in confusion, Devaki gave birth to the divine child, endowed with the auspicious marks, exclusive to Lord Vishnu. The couple saw the incarnation of Vishnu in their effulgent son. Vasudeva considered himself fortunate to be the father of the wonderful son and paid obeisance to the child-god. Brahma, Shiva and other gods assured Devaki about the birth of the Lord as her son, but still she was very apprehensive. She prayed to the child to withdraw all the divine marks from his person, away from public view, in particular from Kamsa. The marks, she was sure, would reveal his identity and her brother would not spare him. The child said there was no need to foresee any danger to him. He told them that he appeared in the divine form before the couple to make it possible for them to associate him with his previous incarnations. So saying he took the form of an ordinary human baby, devoid of divine attributes. He assured them that constant devoted meditation of him would help them reach his abode, the Paramapada.
 
        Parallel to the birth of the Lord to Devaki, Yashoda, Nandas wife, begot Yoga-maya as her daughter. By the influence of the Lords illusory power, Maya, Yashoda was in a state of faint and so she did not know the sex of her child. At the same time, Vasudeva was also released from chains by the divine power. As ordained by the Lord, Vasudeva started towards Nandas house. Now it might be puzzling to find Vasudeva out of the prison with so many guards standing on strict vigil. Lord again by his illusory power sent the guards into a sleepy faint oblivious of what was happening around. The gates threw open on their own and Vasudeva slipped out unnoticed with ease. Rain god was pouring cats and dogs and the river Yamuna was in floods. The entire city was under a thick sheet of darkness. In the Ramayana, the ocean made way for Rama to cross over to Lanka. Similarly, the river Yamuna facilitated Vasudeva to wade through the water by creating a passage. Ananthashesha, the great serpent of Vishnu in Vaikuntha, followed Vasudeva to protect the baby in the basket from the torrential rain by spreading his hood to serve as an umbrella. When he reached Nandas house, the cowherds of the region were under the spell of Maya. Vasudeva left his son by the side of Yashoda and came back to the prison with her baby girl. The gates got locked again and the guards regained consciousness. No one knew the conspiracy that had been carried out against Kamsa.
 
            The cries of the new born alerted the guards. The information reached Kamsa immediately which sent creeps all over him. He thought the dreaded moment had arrived when he was on the precipice of death. Kamsa approached Devaki, with trembling and faltering steps. His countenance showed more fear than hatred. He was taken aback when Devaki pleaded him not to slay the child as it was his niece. Regardless of the sex of the child, wicked Kamsa snatched the baby from her mother as she hugged the child close to her chest. Holding the legs, he tried to smash the baby on a stone. The girl flew out of his hands into the sky in the form of a goddess. She had a bow, arrows, a trident, a shield, a sword, a conch, a discus and a mace in her various hands. The people were astonished at the unusual sight and they at once recognised her as the sister of Lord Vishnu. She mocked at the futile efforts of Kamsa to kill her. Punctuated by sarcasm, she told Kamsa that his adversary was already born elsewhere and hereafter, there was no point in his killing any more babies. The goddess advised him to mend his ways for his own good and then left for the temples awaiting her arrival as the deity to be consecrated.
 
 
 Kamsa and yoga-maya
           
           Kamsa freed Devaki and Vasudeva from the prison. He did not anticipate harm from them, hereafter, as their eighth child happened to be a girl. He profusely apologized for his cruelty. The kind hearted couple did not express any hatred towards the penitent king. He was very happy to have patched up relations with his sister. The king boasted about the thrilling incident in the prison to the allied asura kings. But his supporters shrugged their shoulders with indifference at his enthusiasm. They said, It is true that the prophecy of the divine voice has been falsified by the birth of your sisters daughter. Yet we have to be conscious, the threat from Vishnu has not been completely eliminated and complacency would be very unwise. The information of utmost concern, conveyed by Devakis daughter, has escaped your notice in the excitment of reconciliation. She has unambiguously told you that your enemy has already taken birth elsewhere and is very much alive. We suggest that all babies born in the past ten days be killed, no matter where they are in the country. The Yadus will not pose any danger as the cowherds are ignorant in the use of weapons. Another matter of great importance has to be attended to. Vishnu dwells where righteousness prevails. The noble acts are propagated on earth by brahmanas, the officiating priests, by means of religious rites and sacrifices. The foremost action to be taken would be to bring to a close all religious activities. For this to happen, brahmanas should become extinct. These precautionary measures would also strip the deities of their strength as they thrive on sacrifices. By the absence of virtuous actions, we would have got rid of all possibilities that provide opportunities for Vishnu to be present anywhere on earth. Thus planning a chain of actions to our advantage, we can expect to establish ourselves without any opposition. Thus they put Kamsa to ponder over their suggestions and arrive at a final decision.

Krishna and Balarama
 </body>
</story>