<story>
<body>Chapter 42: Syamantaka retrieved

King of Nighna, Satrajit, was a great friend and a devotee of the sun god. As an expression of his pleasure over their friendship, the sun god made a gift of the celebrated syamantaka jewel to Satrajit. Once when Satrajit went to Dvaraka wearing the jewel round his neck, the inhabitants of the city were engulfed in fear by its blinding radiance. They thought that the sun god was after Krishna, having spied his secret existence among the Yadavas. They reported their fear to Krishna. He explained to them that it was Satrajit resplendent with the lustre of the jewel on his body. The unique quality of the jewel was that it could ward off famine, evils, premature death and any other calamity of the person possessing it. When Krishna asked Satrajit to give the jewel to the king of the Yadavas, he refused to part with it.
 
One day, Satrajits brother Prasenajit wore the jewel while going hunting in the forest. When he did not return, Satrajit suspected Krishna for killing him for the sake of the jewel. This rumour spread like wild fire maligning the blemishless character of Krishna. To clear the wrong notion, Krishna set out in search of Prasenajit. He soon found Prasenajit and his horse mauled by a lion, which in turn had been killed by a bear. Finding the dark cave of the bear, Krishna asked his men to stay outside, while he went in. There he found the bear cubs playing with the jewel, as if it were a toy. Krishna waited for a chance to get the jewel. The caretaker bear was stunned at the brilliance of the person in the cave and in fear shrieked which alerted Jambavan, the king of the bears. To ward off the danger to his cubs, Jambavan impulsively started a fight with Krishna, not noticing his divine form. The combat continued for eighteen days, at the end of which the bear was drained of his strength by a blow from Krishnas fist. Feebly looking up at the man before him, the bear recognised him as the Paramapurusha Vishnu. In the Ramavatara of Vishnu, Rama had sought the help of monkeys and bears of whom Jambavan was one of Ramas prominent advisers. They constructed a bridge across the ocean to reach Lanka to rescue Sita from the ten headed Ravana. Regretting his callousness towards the Supreme Lord, Jambavan began to sing his praise. Receiving the jewel, Krishna told him that the jewel was only an excuse. He had left his men outside and entered the cave alone only to relieve Jambavan from a brahmanas curse. He expressed his gratitude and received Krishnas blessings.
 
The people outside waited for twelve days impatiently for Krishnas return.Then they concluded that he had been killed by the bear. Depressed at losing Krishna, they went back home. The news about Krishnas death was a terrible shock to his parents and all the citizens. Immersed in inconsolable sorrow, they cursed Satrajit for being the cause of the disaster. With a ray of hope, everyone prayed to Durga to save the life of their Janardana [Krishna] and help his safe return. As if in answer to their prayers, Krishna came back to Dvaraka but not alone. He had Jambavati, the daughter of Jambavan, with him, who was given in marriage by her father as a reverential gift.
 
Krishna called Satrajit to take back his jewel. He narrated in detail as to how he had secured it. Satrajit was ashamed for the aspersions he had cast on Krishnas character, without ascertaining the truth. The guilt feeling denied him peace of mind. He was thinking of making amends for his blunder. Giving his dear daughter,  Satyabhama, in marriage to Krishna and also gifting the jewel appeared to be the best reconciliation he could think of. Krishna accepted the hand of Satyabhama but with regard to the jewel he said,This is a gift to you from your friend, the sun god, for your devotion. Therefore, you are the legitimate owner. You must retain it as our king. Under your able protection, we are blessed to be the fortunate subjects. We will merely enjoy the benefits of the jewel. With these words, Satrajit and Krishna parted as friends.
 
General expectation would be that the confusion created by the syamantaka was over with the hand shake of Satrajit and Krishna. But it was not to be so because it had to be instrumental in rolling of a couple of heads. More than that, Akrura, the trusted friend of Krishna, had to be reprimanded for his dishonesty with regard to the jewel. For the sake of the jewel, he had changed his loyalty like a chameleon that alters its colour to its surrounding. The change of attitude occurred when Krishna was in Hastinapur with the Kauravas, to grieve the death of his Pandava relations in the Jatugriha [house of lac].
 
Akrura and Kirtivarman advised Shatadhanu to kill Satrajit and get possession of the syamantaka jewel. Misguided Shatadhanu did likewise and obtained the jewel. Satyabhama went to Hastinapur to inform Krishna about the cruel killing of her father by Shatadhanu. Krishna came back and resolved to kill him. Akrura and Kirtivarman refused to help Shatadhanu as they had witnessed the prowess of the Lord on many occasions. Shatadhanu, finding himself left on the lurch by the two traitors he had trusted, handed over the jewel to Akrura and made an escape. Krishna and Balarama chased him till the outskirts of Mythila. Krishna killed Shatadhanu but, to his disappointment, could not find the jewel with him. Krishna felt very sorry for killing poor Shatadhanu as it turned out to be futile. Balarama advised his brother to go back to Dvaraka to find out the person in whose custody it might have been left. Balarama, in the meanwhile, decided to stay in Mythila with his friend King Janaka for a few years, where he enjoyed the honoured hospitality. It was during this long period of stay, Duryodhana underwent the training of the use of the mace from Balarama.
 
Krishna went back to Dvaraka with the news of the death of Shatadhanu and the jewel still missing which evoked mixed feelings of sorrow and disappointment. Akrura and Kirtivarman went away from Dvaraka out of fear as nothing could be a secret from Krishna. Since there were unprecedented evils and calamities occurring, the people linked it with the departure of Akrura. The reason for the connection of the two was that Akruras father and his mother Gandhivi were believed to have brought showers when Indra withdrew the rains by his power. From that time, it was accepted that Akrura had inherited the powers of his parents to avert natural calamities. But Krishna thought it to be due to the disappearance of the syamantaka. Krishna brought back Akrura and after the formality of extending hospitality was over, he came straight to the point. Without mincing words, he told Akrura he was absolutely sure of the jewel being in his possession. He said he could keep it by all means but he would have to make a public confession particularly before his elder brother. He further told Akrura that the excessive flow of gold, for the altars during the countless sacrifices he has been performing, exposed him. Only that jewel had the merit of producing uninterrupted supply of gold in such large quantities. Finding himself check mated by Krishna, Akrura, like a dog with his tail between his legs, brought out the effulgent syamantaka jewel from under his upper garment and gave it to Krishna.
Interesting Anecdotes

 

Lac palace: The Pandavas were always considered as thorns in their life by the Kauravas. They were conspiring against the Pandavas and finding means of getting them out of the way. Dhritharashtra planned a joint excursion to Varanavrata for attending some festivities. Duryodhana was inspired by his wicked ideas. Under the pretext of organising a comfortable nights stay for his cousins in Varanavrata, he had a castle of lac built with all possible comforts. The hypocritical concern of the Kauravas was, in fact, one of their conspiracies to put an end to the perenial problem in the form of their cousins. They had not provided any exit for the palace. So, when the highly inflammable lac was set on fire with the entrance closed, the Pandavas would be burnt, with no way to escape. Vidura, the wise uncle, got wind of the treacherous plan. Without the knowledge of Duryodhana, he got a secret under ground passage to the palace prepared. He advised the Pandavas, in private, to escape through the subterranean exit well in advance of the fire in the castle. The Pandavas followed the instructions and with Kunti, their mother, reached a safe destination and remained in hiding in a forest nearby. But before they left, Bhima set fire to the castle so that the Kauravas would not know of their escape. Unfortunately, the builder of the castle, named Purochana and a Nishada family consisting of a woman with her five drunken sons got trapped inside in two different rooms. They were charred to death beyond recognition. Mistaking the burnt remains of the Nishada family as the Pandavas with their mother, the Kauravas were exhilarated at the demise of their cousins and gloated over their new found freedom. Krishna was aware of the real happening but made sure it was not leaked out by any chance. He too joined the Kauravas in the condolence gathering and pretended to grieve the death of the Pandu family.
 

Lac Palace in flames Pandavas escape</body>
</story>