<story>
<body>Chapter 47: Wishes of Devaki

            Devaki had never reconciled to the death of her sons at the hands of Kamsa. She heard that her sons Krishna and Balarama had brought to life the dead son of their preceptor. With great hope she requested them, You have taken birth here to lighten the burden of mother earth. I, your mother also carry a heavy burden in my heart, an unbearable sorrow which could be relieved by you. You have also resuscitated your gurus son. Could you do a similar act of kindness for me by reviving my dead sons? Very much moved by their mothers grief, they instantly repaired to the Netherlands, to the kingdom of the daitya king Bali.
 
            Bali was pleased to offer his respects to the two brothers and expressed his gratitude for their visit to a wicked persons region. He said, My constant prayer is to seek shelter under your trees of benevolence, you who are the Universal protectors and enjoy the fruits of mercy you drop down to us. I would then have cleansed my sins and instilled spiritual life within me. Besides this, I have no other aspirations. I now stand before you with folded hands, eager to serve you to the best of my abilities. I await your commands.
 
            Krishna told him the purpose of his visit was to revive his six brothers and present them before his pining mother Devaki. He explained to Bali the misconception under which Devaki was mourning. He told Bali the past life of his brothers. Prajapati Marichi had six sons by Uma who were cursed by Brahma. Brahma created Sarasvati as pretty as the apsaras Tilottama. Captivated by her beauty, he decided to make her his consort. The six sons of Marichi went into a fit of laughter to find a person desirous of marrying his own daughter. Brahma was angered by the flippant attitude of the boys towards him. He cursed them to be born as asuras. Though in reality the six sons of Marichi were born as the sons of the Bhoja king Hiranyakashipu, they were placed in Devakis womb by the power of Yoga-maya. Not knowing the secret, Devaki thought they were her sons killed by Kamsa. Depression due to his mothers mourning and also her pleadings for the revival of her dead sons had impelled Krishna to come to Bali for the boys. Krishna said he would take the six boys residing in his kingdom to let Devaki see them alive just once. Then by his grace, they would be freed from the effect of the curse and enter the order of the pious.
 

 Devaki gets back her sons
            Bali readily agreed and Krishna took them to his mother who was overjoyed with happiness. Her fondling of the sons revealed, to what extent her motherly emotions had been bottled up all these years. Everyone was thrilled at the reunion, when their mutual affection manifested to the maximum. Finding all round satisfaction, Krishna freed his brothers from the curse. Due to their association with their mother, denied so far, having eaten out of the plate of Balarama and the contact with the sacred body of Krishna, the six boys became spiritually enlightened. Paying their respects to their parents and brothers, they moved towards the celestial region. Devaki was astonished to watch the miraculous happenings before her eyes and was convinced it could not have been possible without the divine power of Krishna.

 </body>
</story>