<story>
<body>Shukracharya revived Bali back to life after his death in the devasura battle. Bali changed his life for the better. He gave away all his wealth to his preceptor and became the descendent of the Bhrigu race. The descendents of Bhrigu were appreciative of his sincere devotion. They inspired him to perform the vishvajit sacrifice to fulfill his desire to be the Lord of heaven. The oblations were poured into the sacrificial fire. Then a golden chariot having a lion as the emblem, a quiver with inexhaustible arrows and an ethereal bow came out. The Bhrigus infused great spiritual energy into Bali. His grand father Prahlada gave him a garland of unfading lotus while from his preceptor he received a conch.
 
With a huge battalion of eminent generals, Bali marched confidently towards the heavenly city of Indra, striking terror in heaven and earth. He saw the grandeur of the city where the architectural expertise of Vishvakarma was evident. In addition to the adequate structural fortification, the city had a natural protection. It was guarded against entry of wicked, lustful, greedy unrighteous people. Bali stationed his army encircling the entire city and blew his conch signaling aggression. Indra felt his throne was shaken by the loud fierce sound. Bali appeared to be a formidable foe with overflowing self confidence and power. Indra was amazed at the strength and wondered how he came to possess it. Brihaspati cleared the doubt and said, Indra! Bali has been loaded with the spiritual energy of the scions of the Bhrigus. Destiny being favourable to him at the present moment, his luck is sky-rocketing. Only Sri Hari can stand up against him. It is advisable to remain in hiding outside heaven, till the opportune time, when Bali himself would work towards his down fall. The deities, the sons of Aditi, acted on Brihaspatis advice. Assuming unidentifiable forms, they evacuated Amaravati, the city of the gods. With the way cleared for Bali, he established himself as the lord of the three worlds. Bali was renowned far and wide. He was very prosperous with the favour of the Bhrigus. The brahmanas of the Bhrigus, overjoyed with the victory of their disciple with the power of the vishvajit sacrifice, desired that he performed hundred ashvamedha sacrifices. Bali started the sacrifices in earnest to establish himself firmly as the supreme monarch in the newly acquired dominion.
 
Aditi was immensely depressed over the asuras occupying her sons city. Kashyapa rising from his samadhi, deep meditation, arrived at Aditis hermitage after a long time. Seeing his wife very sad, he was anxious to know if all was well with her. He enquired if she had dutifully carried out her services to the brahmanas, guests and offered oblations to sacrificial fires. She assured him there had been no lapse anywhere. She was miserable about the exile of her sons from Amaravati as also the accession of their territory by the asuras. She pleaded her all knowing husband to guide her towards the best way of propitiation of the Lord. She had great faith in the compassionate Lords readiness to help his distressed devotees with outstretched hands. He was the only ray of hope in her gloomy life shrouded in sorrow. He had to restore the legitimate right of her sons over their property. Kashyapa said that Sri Hari would wipe her tears without fail. He instructed her to observe the vow of payovrata which will grant her the desired result. He explained that his grandfather Brahma had taught him the procedure, when he was desirous of having progeny. If the vow was observed with strict adherence to the rules of austerity, the Almighty would soon fulfill her desire. He instructed her that she should begin on the first day of the bright fortnight continued through thirteen days in the month of Phalguna. He also told her as to what should be done and those to be avoided, laying out clearly the entire procedure.
 
            Aditi meticulously concentrated on the observance of the vow. At the conclusion of the vow, she was taken unawares by a most wonderful experience of her life. She witnessed the Great Purusha Vishnu appear before her eyes. She was so stunned at the grandeur of the sight that except shedding tears of joy, she could not express her gratitude otherwise. She silently bowed before him for his extraordinary favour. The Lord said, I am aware that you wish to see your sons prosperous again. But the pity is, the asuras are unconquerable at present by the energy of the brahmanas of the Bhrigu race. But your flawless observance of the vow has to be productive. I will soon be born as your son to save your present sons, the eldest of them being Indra. You must keep this secret to yourself if our plan has to succeed. Brahma went into ecstasy on knowing that the Lord was to enter the womb of Aditi. He praised him as the rescue boat for a drowning man.
 
            The Lord was born to Aditi on the shravana dvadashi, the twelvth day of the bright fortnight of the month bhadrapada. Having the mark of srivatsa and adorned by the kaustubha gem, he was born under the influence of the shravana star at an hour called abhijit, conducive to victory. This day goes by the name of vijaya dvadashi. Lord Sri Hari, resplendent with his glorious form, transformed himself into a dwarf brahmana boy to the astonishment of the couple Aditi and Kashyapa. Investiture of the thread ceremony was performed and the sacred Gayatri Mantra taught. Vamana, meaning dwarf, now a full fledged brahmacharin, received the initiation into the Vedic scriptures.
 
 Vamana, with an umbrella and a kamandalu of water in hand, set off for the horse sacrifice of Bali. Bali and other Bhrigu brahmanas assembled there got up to pay obeisance to the brahmacharin. He was duly offered a seat and Bali washed his feet, an honour shown to revered personalities. The initial formalities over, Bali and the brahmanas rendered the occasion auspicious. Bali addressed Vamana thus, O holy brahmana! You have sanctified my sacrifice by your arrival and I am obliged to you to have given me an opportunity to wash your feet. This consecrated water is capable of washing away the sins of everyone including mine. Please let me know how best I can express my gratitude. I guess you have something in mind which you seek. You have just got to ask and it shall be granted. Bali offered the gift of a cow, a house, gold and many prosperous villages. In reply, Vamana said, Who does not know the charitable nature of your predecessors. They never retracted from their promise. This is ample evidence of their commitment to truth. You are in no way lacking in any of these noble qualities. I am grateful for the enormous gifts offered by you. But land measuring just three strides by my feet is all I need. I am sure you will grant me that. Bali was carried away by the praise showered by the boy that blinded him from the trick behind the request. Bali replied, You seem to be an intelligent boy. I am the undisputed lord of the three worlds. When I can afford to gift a whole continent, you have asked for only three paces with your small feet. I will not force you to make a second request. Therefore, I will grant you sufficient land for a decent living. The boy replied, You are a generous person. Think of me too. I will prove myself unworthy if I am not satiated with what I need. Craving for more will indicate my greed. No one should promote ones acquisitive instinct even if he be the lord of the three worlds. Contentment leads to liberation, dissatisfaction to misery. Need and wealth must be maintained at equilibrium in our lives. So the three strides of land will be adequate to serve my purpose. Bali mockingly smiled at the boy who was naive to reject his generous gift and insist on having a tiny piece of land. He lifted his kamandalu, the pot of water to solemnize his promise of granting the three paces of land.
 
            Shrewd and vicious Shukracharya smelt a rat in the mysterious appearance of the Brahmana boy. He could see Vishnu in that dwarf, who, he knew for sure, had come there for the cause of the gods. He tried to stop Bali from the commitment, pointing to the possible danger to his sovereignty. He warned the king, You are being deluded by the boy with his apparent insignificant demand. Know him to be no other than Vishnu himself, come as a dwarf to deceive you. I am sure he would measure the earth and the heaven with his two strides and the mid region by his expansive body. May I ask how you are going to provide for the third stride? Non fulfillment of promise to a brahmana would destroy the asuras. The infernal region will become your residence with no saving alternative. Let me remind you that the monetary requirements for the completion of the sacrifices will be very large. Do not forget the responsibility you owe to the subjects which is your primary commitment as a king. Their welfare is solely dependent on the kings intelligent and right disbursement of finances. If the wealth in its entirety is lost, providing them even bare subsistence would become impossible. So take my advice seriously and not fall into the trickery of this brahmana boy. Bali tried to assimilate the wise cautioning of his preceptor. At the end of a serious deliberation, he humbly conveyed his decision to his guru, I am beholden to you for your concerned advice. Without any disrespect to you, I must confess that I beg to differ. I have given my promise to the brahmana and do not wish to go back on it. Great personalities like Dadhichi and Shibi gave up their lives for the good of others. Generous souls as well as worthy recipients are very rare. When a man dies, he leaves behind all his possessions. His merits alone accompany him. I am now at the cross roads when a wise decision is required to lead me along the right path of merit. Why should I not sacrifice whole heartedly a portion of my earth during my lifetime? Being the grandson of Prahlada and a celebrated king myself, I do not want to carry the blemish of breach of promise for the greed of material prosperity. If he is really Vishnu, I do not think he would descend to the level of coveting my kingdom by trickery and forfeit his reputation as Lord Supreme. This boy seems to be least interested in grabbing the sovereignty from me. If he has any such intentions, let him be brave to fight and win the lordship. If he is an impostor, I wish to slay such a person. These words of Bali did not appeal to Shukracharya. He took it as disobedience arising from high mindedness. May be it was the decree of Providence that sent the guru into a fit of rage to curse his disciple to roll down from the heights of prosperity.
 
            The honest soul, undeterred by the curse, gifted the land to the brahmana. Balis wife Vindhyavali happily joined her husband in his noble act. Even the celestials, always with their daggers drawn against the asuras, sent down showers of flowers applauding the guileless mans gesture. Lord Vishnu at once accepted the gift from Bali. He grew into a gigantic form, from the size of a dwarf. One stride took care of the earth. With his second, he measured the heaven up to the satyaloka while the mid region was covered by his huge body and arms. Brahma and other gods washed the feet of the Lord when he was taking the step across the heaven. That sanctified water runs as the sacred Ganges in the three worlds now. There was nothing left for the third step. The asuras were enraged at the position to which their king had been reduced. They wanted to attack the enemy but were ably resisted by the attendants of Vishnu. Bali too advised them to desist as the time was not favourable to the asuras. Patience was the need of the hour till lady luck turned towards them as in the previous occasion. Discontent with the command of their king, the generals withdrew to the Netherlands. Garuda, Vishnus vehicle, tied down Bali with the noose of varuna, while the horse sacrifice of Bali was still in progress. Amidst loud wailing by the asuras, the Lord returning to the size of the Vamana addressed the imprisoned king thus, I have covered the worlds by my two strides. There is not an inch for my third step. How are you going to fulfill your agreement with me? Divine decree for default of promise would be the infernal region. Excessive arrogance over your wealth induced you to make an open offer to me. Time has come for you to swallow your pride. You have to reap the reward for being presumptuous. Vishnu had no grudge against Bali to punish him. He wanted to show the world the resolute character of Bali. The employment of the severest remonstration did not unnerve him and he stood calm till the Lord had finished speaking. He said, Do not doubt the honesty of my words. Lord! I will prove my genuine intentions here and now. Place your foot on my head for your third stride. It is the best offering I think I have made to you so far, as compared to the other things in my possession. I am not afraid of any calamity that the world has in store for me. I am not nervous about the punishment you may subject me to. Now I have understood that the worldly relationships with our kith and kin would fade away some day or the other. It is futile to nurture these attachments. I am at present in a position to comprehend the depth of spiritual life. My grandfather, Prahlada, was inhumanly tortured by his own father Hiranyakashipu. The only fault on his part was his steadfast devotion to you, Lord Vishnu. His unfathomable wisdom had no impact on me all these years and I was infatuated by the illusive prosperity I saw around me. Now, I have realized what his life had tried to teach me. It was that you are the only assured resort worthy of aspiration in a mans life. My accidental encounter with you has been a blessing as I have surrendered myself at your lotus feet. Belonging to the lineage of Prahlada, I cannot afford to malign the prestigious reputation by being branded ignoble and called the black sheep of the family.
 
            All those assembled there, were astonished at the mature exposition of Bali to Vamana, when it was intercepted by the arrival of the honourabe Prahlada. Bali could not prostrate before his grandfather as he was in captivity. He bowed his head to express his humble respects. The tears flowing from his eyes, lowered in shame for his previous insolent behaviour towards Vishnu, were more expressive of his repentance than what words would have conveyed. Prahlada was overwhelmed with joy at the sight of the Supreme Lord. He prostrated before the Lord and expressed his gratitude for bringing back his child Bali who had strayed away from the right path. He said, You elevated him to the position of Indra by the vishvajit sacrifice. But he was not ready for such honour. He lost his direction in pride. Dethroning him was the turning point in his life that brought Bali back to his senses. Great people get caught in the maze of delusion and wander aimlessly drifting away from you. What to speak of this immature Bali? O Lord! You have retrieved my child from a disastrous downfall. I shall ever be beholden to you for your mercy. Balis wife made a very impressive speech loaded with high philosophy. She said, You are the Lord of this universe which is your creative sport. Its contents also belong to you. The notion of mine and thine is illusory which pervades all living beings without exception. In ignorance, people offer you things on which they have no rightful claim. We ourselves are the outcome of your maya. How can we then assert our ownership on anything in this universe? Power of creation, preservation and destruction are exclusive to you and we are mere puppets.
 
            Finally, Brahma pleaded clemency for Bali. He said, O Lord! You are the cosmic being who liberates those who seek you in panic and fear of spiritual ruin. Here is a man who has surrendered all that he thought belonged to him. Without an iota of remorse he has placed at your feet all the fruits of his meritorious actions. Even his body is not his anymore. O merciful Lord, in what way does he deserve the sufferance of bondage? Please show your kindness to this poor soul and release him. To this Vamana replied, I do not have to use my harsh ways of reformation with devoted people who seldom fall a prey to delusion. Only persons afflicted by vanity and pride wantonly despise the virtuous blessed life. I divest them of their wealth that acts as the pride insinuating intoxicant. People who are slaves to infatuation are tamed by me to come down to reality from their attitude of disregard to everyone, even to me. But Bali has adhered to truthfulness. His honest spirit was not sullied despite the long chain of set backs like losing his sovereignty, forsaken by his kinsmen, and cursed by his preceptor. My ambiguous lectures on righteousness did not detract him. His exemplary character has earned him the distinguished place in my realm. Before I embrace him into my domain, I want to fulfill his desire to reign as Indra, the lord of paradise. This will happen only in the savarni manvantara. Till then he can rule over the sutala region beautified by Vishvakarma, the architect of heaven. I offer myself to guard his fort from harm. With daityas in attendance, he will enjoy sovereignty. Any transgression of his command will be properly dealt with by my discus. If by some unexpected influence of the danavas, demoniac ideas try to raise their heads to obstruct Balis righteous thinking, I will instantly nip them in the bud. With folded hands, Bali, in a choked voice, expressed how grateful he was for the Lords benevolence. He said, "With my despicable past, I am not fit to call myself the Lords devotee. You have chosen to bestow on me a favour even beyond the reach of the gods. Prahlada expressed his gratitude to the Lord for his unprejudiced recognition of people who have reformed even though born in the wretched race of asuras, predominantly given to evil ways. The admirable quality of the Lord is that he acts as the wish yielding tree for his devotees. The Lord directed Prahlada to accompany his grandson happily to sutala. He instructed Shukracharya to complete the sacrifice started by Bali without a flaw. To the happiness of Aditi and Kashyapa, Vamana crowned Indra as the king of the three worlds. Since Vamana was the younger brother of Indra, he became Upendra. Indra took Upendra to heaven and under his able guidance ruled for a long time.</body>
</story>