<story>
<body>Aditi, Dakshas daughter, begot Vivasvan, the sun god, by Kashyapa. Vaivasvata Manu, also known as Shraddhadeva, was Vivasvans son by his wife Sanjana. Before the birth of his ten sons, the eldest being Ikshvaku, the childless Manu requested the great preceptor Vasishta to perform a sacrifice in honour of Mitra and Varuna, the gods who grant a son.
 
            The preceptor of the solar race ordered the priest to commence the sacrifice. While the priest was invoking the gods, Manus wife, Shraddha, approached him with a request to propitiate the gods for a daughter. With this request hovering in his mind, the priest poured the oblations into the sacrificial fire. Though he did not make any effort to ensure the birth of a daughter, the distraction of his mind was enough to alter the motive of the sacrifice. As a result, a girl was born to the utter disappointment of Manu. She was named Ila. Manu was perplexed to believe the potent Vedic mantras falsifying their power. Manu asked Vasishta to probe into the cause of reversal of the result. Vasishtas sharp brain promptly found it was due to the distraction caused by the request of Shraddha. He used his spiritual power to please Lord Hari and secured his blessings to transform the girl into a boy to the immense satisfaction of Manu. He was named Sudyumna.
 
            Manus desire was fulfilled. But Sudyumna was destined to go through lot of problems regarding his sex. It kept undergoing change every now and then due to reasons not in his control. Once he went hunting in the forest at the foot of mount Meru. At that moment, Shiva and Uma were together enjoying each others company. Instantly, Sudyumna became a girl at the very entrance of the forest. All the followers were changed into women. Even the horses took the form of mares. [The sudden change in sex was made possible in yonder years by magical powers but today medical science has provided technology to cater to the whimsicalities of man].
 
            Let us now pause at this juncture to see the reason behind the miraculous power of the forest to convert into females, men stepping into its precincts. Once, some sages entered the forest to pay their respects to Shiva. The sages were not aware that Uma was resting her head on Shivas lap. Her dress was slightly out of place. The sages withdrew immediately, knowing it as intrusion into their privacy. Uma too jumped up and made herself presentable. Yet she could not get over the shame of having appeared before males in an indecent state. Shiva found a way to save his dear wife from embarrassment in future. He ordained that thenceforth, that particular land would be out of bounds for males. Any transgression by men into the private area would change them into women instantly. Sudyumna innocently stepped into the forbidden land and bore the brunt of Shivas pronouncement.
 

 Vasishtha prays to Shiva
          
            Now back to Ilas story. She continued to roam the forest with her female friends after her transformation from Sudyumna. While in the vicinity of Budhas hermitage, both Ila and Budha were attracted to each other. [Budha as the son of Tara and Soma]. Budha, of the lunar race, begot a son Pururava by Ila. Now Ila began to yearn for her form as Sudyumna and her thoughts went to Vasishta. By his yogic powers, he came before Ila and was upset about what had happened. He engaged himself in the propitiation of Shiva. Shiva was pleased but could not revoke his previous utterance completely. He suggested a special compromise. He agreed to allow Ila to assume her male form of Sudyumna alternate months, which appeared to be fair enough. Sudyumna became the king. Not willing to reveal the secret of his female form, he went into hiding during those months. He was an efficient king but people were dissatisfied by his frequent mysterious disappearance. He reigned successfully till his old age. He retired to the forest after appointing Pururava as the king.
 </body>
</story>