<story>
<body>hapter 30: Exposition - self-surrender

 

Bhagavatam describes self surrender in a beautiful way that has made the difficult concept easy for common comprehension.
 
            Once, the damsels of Vraja undertook a severe vow invoking Goddess Katyayani for a whole month starting on the first day of the Hemanta season. Each morning, they bathed in the river Kalindi followed by a devotional worship of a sand image of the goddess on the river bank. With flowers, fruits, rice and other pleasing articles, the gopis would pray to be united with the cowherd son of Nanda. They would call on every house, collect the friends and sing in chorus, hymns in praise of the Lord as they proceeded to the river bank for observing the vow. Each would imagine herself to be with the Lord, though it was joint singing.
 

 Krishna demonstrates Self surrender
           
            One day, they left their clothes on the bank and stepped into the water for their ablution. Krishna stole their clothes and perched himself on the kadamba tree to test their determined dedication and single minded devotion to God. He asked them to come out of water to collect the clothes from him. They took it as a joke and were appreciative of Krishnas sense of humour. They felt ashamed to appear naked before Krishna. Going neck deep into water, they pleaded him to return their clothes. Krishna insisted on their coming out of water if they wanted the clothes. Compelled by Krishna, the maidens came out bashfully covering themselves with their hands. But Krishna would not agree until they raised their hands above their heads in obeisance. When the gopis humbly did as commanded, Krishna returned the clothes.
 
Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita says:
 ?????????????????? ???? ?? ???: ?????????? | 
 ?????? ?????????????????? ?????????? ????????? ||
 
 Ananyashchintayanto mam ye janah paryupasate
Thesham nityabhiyukthanam yogakshemam vahamyaham
 
Those who propitiate me consistently desiring to attain me, with single minded devotion [with an undistracted mind] I take the responsibility of their worldly as well as spiritual welfare.
 
In the Bhagavatam, Krishna explained to the gopis, in simple words the philosophy contained in the above verse of the Bhagavad Gita. In this verse, the Lord explains that if people propitiate the minor gods with the aim to acquire small benefits, those will not help them to emancipation.On the other hand, people would be caught in repeated birth and death in this world, subjected to incessant problems. Discarding all the small gains and seeking the divine feet of the Lord as the one and only remedy, man will reach the bliss of the ultimate happiness. Realising that the Lord is the Supreme Being, if people seek his grace, God will, on his own, admit them to his realm from where there is no return to this world. God will grant emancipation to the supplicant at the appropriate time. Till then, he will have to abide his time and live in this world. During that period, God will protect his welfare, lest he becomes desperate and loses faith in God.
With reference to what he expected of the gopis when he compelled them to give up the reservations oppressing their minds, he said it was to help them understand the sublimity of self surrender to God. He said, My dear gopis! It was a practical demonstration conducted by me to dispel the petty feelings that obstruct the path of sharanagati, self surrender. You have fallen at my feet without any inhibition. That is an indication of being free from ego, ahamkara as it is called. Such a person is not affected by happiness or sorrow, prosperity or diversity, shame or any of the feelings or emotions attributed to human beings. The possessive instinct vanishes and the feeling of oneness manifests. The Lord has reiterated the truth,' ?????? ??????????(VASUDHAIVA KUTUMBAKAM), the world is a single family. He further continued, Observing the vow, you have successfully disciplined yourselves. Your prostration before me now, has further chastened you, insulating your mind against emotional reaction to worldly matters, just as frying prevents the corn from sprouting. Your mind is fixed firm in your quest for God. My test on you has convinced me of the purity of your hearts. As an expression of my appreciation of your absolute dedication I shall reward you with my company tomorrow night. The gopis were thrilled beyond measure as their sincere vow had borne a favourable result. They returned home with contentment. A short reference to Shukas character will strengthen our belief in the truth which Krishna has explained. Once when the ladies, bathing in the river, were shy to be naked before Vyasa, they experienced no such feelings in front of his son Shuka. When asked for the reason, they said, Shuka, though a young boy of sixteen, has risen above the mundane world of emotions. So his presence does not evoke any undesirable feelings in us just the way the sight of a woman does not mentally disquietened him. 
 

Shuka has no emotions
 
            Tamil saint poetess Andal lived long after Krishna. In her famous string of verses, the Tiruppavai, she visualizes herself in Brindavana during the time of Krishna. She imagines performing the Katyayani vow with the gopis from mid December to mid January, the Tamil month of Margazhi, which happens to be the Hemanta season. She describes in thirty verses the entire procedure of the vow, associating herself in the service of the Lord, pleading him to bestow his grace and fulfill her desire of everlasting union with him.
 

Sri Andal
 
               ??????????????? ????????? ????????* ??? 
   ?????????????????????? ????????????* 
   ??????? ?????? ???????? ????????? ??????? ?? 
   ???????????????? ????????? ??????*
   ??????? ?????????????????? ????????!
   ??????????????? ????????????* ?????????
   ???????? ??????; ?????? ??????????????
   ???????? ??????? ??????????????????
 
  Chitranchirukale vandunnai sevitthu un
            Potramaraiyadiye pottrum porullkellai
            Pettrammeitthunnum kulatthirpirandu ni
            Kuttrevalengalai Kollamarpohadu
            Ittraiparaikollvanandrukann govinda
            Ettraikkumezhezhezhpiravikkum undannodu
            Uttromeyavom unakke namatcchaivom
            Mattrainamkamangal matrelorempavai    
           
Hear the purpose of our coming early in the morning to prostrate at your lotus like feet having a golden hue. Having been born in the community of cowherds that earns its living by grazing cattle, you cannot forsake us who are ever ready to obey your commands. Today, we seek you for the parai, the drum but we have other aspirations besides that. O Govinda! We pray that our relationship should exist not just today but be everlasting for many generations to come [twice seven births]. We want to serve you, no one else but you. Please destroy other undesirable cravings present in us.
 </body>
</story>