<story>
<body>Chapter 23: Maryada Purushottama

        
 Sita Rama Lakshmana Hanuman

            Purushottama Rama, son of king Dasharatha, was the model king of Ayodhya. His rapport with his subjects emphasizes the good governance of a perfect king just as an efficient father, the head of the family, manages to maintain unity and holds tight the close bond of affection among his family members.

            Rama, as the incarnation of Vishnu, estabishes the fundamental principle of Varnashrama Dharma, by adhering to the performance of his duties diligently as expected of a monarch. He exhibited the importance of strong determined character in an effective king. The inability of a sovereign head to conduct himself with discipline would lead to chaos similar to the kingdom of God, without the God himself. Rama was the eldest son of Dasharatha, born to the first queen Kausalya. Bharata was the son of Kaikeyi, the king's favoured queen. Lakshmana and Shatrughna were the sons of Sumitra, the third wife of Dasharatha.

          Rama started on his expedition as a kshatriya warrior at the age of sixteen. He was called upon by sage Vishvamitra to help him against the asuras who were obstructing the sacrificial proceedings. Equipped with bow and arrow, accompanied by the knowledge of the science of mantras for invoking powerful weapons ana also alert to the sound of vibration, Rama could follow the adversary wherever he might be. The brahmastra was the ultimate weapon.Vishvamitra was mightily pleased with the successful performance of the young boy, ably assisted by his constant companion brother Lakshmana.

            [The variety of weapons used in the final war with Ravana, reveals the existence of missiles  as early as the treta yuga. Then the weapons were shot by invoking the relevent mantras but now we have the modern technology to aim the weapons at the target through remote control.]

            Vishvamitra then led Rama to the svayamvara of Sita, the daughter of king Janaka of Mithila. The condition for the svayamvara was the successful stringing of the Shiva Dhanush. Janaka had recieved the formidable bow from Shiva and the Lord himself had ackowledged that the person who could string the bow would possess extraordinary power and strength. On the advice of the sage, Rama entered the competition to try his capability to lift the bow which he did with ease. When none could even move the weapon, here was a teenager who effortlessly flexed the bow to string it. But his extraordinary strength snapped the bow into two with a loud noise. Rama thus succeeded in winning the hand of Sita. She was actually Lakshmi, the consort of Vishnu. She had descended on earth to assist the Lord in his incarnation as Rama to vanquish the demon Ravana, the terror of married women.



Rama breaks Shiva bow

            The marriage of the four brothers was performed, with brides found for all of them in the Janaka family. They returned home happily with their wives. Soon there  was a terrible, unexpected jolt in the life of the prince of Ayodhya. While King Dasharatha was making arrangements for the coronation of Rama, which had all round acclaim, Kaikeyi's maid Manthara intruded to foil the  king's plans. She poisoned the mind of her mistress against Rama's forthcoming elevation as the heir and persuaded her against agreeing to the proposal. She suggested that the queen could use the two boons recieved by her for nursing her wounded husband during the battle between Indra and the asuras. It was a gift of gratitude from the king for Kaikeyi's devoted services.

            Kaikeyi was equally affectionate to Rama as to her own son Bharata. She was thrilled to hear about the coronation of Rama and reprimanded her maid for nuturing evil intentions. But Manthara pulled the strings of emotion to influence the queen. She refused to give up her persistence and brought about a complete change of attitude in the unmaligned mind of Kaikeyi. As directed by the wicked woman, Kaikeyi lay in the kopagriha, as if in wrath, when the king came to convey her the delightful news. She vehemently expressed her dissent to her husband's arbitrary decision to declare Rama as his successor. She demanded that Rama should be sent to the forest for fourteen years and her son Bharata be made the king instead. This, she said, was her encashment of the two boons given by the king. The king fell unconscious on hearing the harsh words. When he regained consciousness, he sobbed,"I have placed myself in a state similar to a man who suffers the consequences of his misdeeds in the previous birth. In the earlier occasion, I granted you the two boons because you brought me out of death. But at that time, I did not realise you would use them as a weapon to kill me now. I am bound to truth. Though Rama is dearer to me than anything else in the world, I cannot trangress my word of promise and prove myself ungrateful."

          Dasharatha found himself tongue tied by overwhelming grief and could not make known the heartless decision to Rama. Kaikeyi was thrilled at winning over her husband and, with a heart deserted of all kind feelings, burst out with excitement to convey the change in the king's decision. Rama, composed as always, recieved the news without an iota of grief and whole-heartedly agreed to obey the commands of his father. The whole country was in sorrow about the unpalatable bitter reversal of destiny. Advice to claim his legitamacy to the throne could not influence Rama to be motivated to unrighteousness. He chose to stick to his obligation and reverence towards his father. Lakshmana and Sita insisted on accompanying him. The trio started on their journey to the forest which claimed the life of the sorrowing father Dasharatha.

            Bharata returned to Ayodhya from his maternal uncle's house and was shocked on hearing the terrible developments at home in his absence. Annoyed with his mother's discriminating mentality, Bharata broke his cordial relations with her and rushed to the forest to make amends for Kaikeyi's devilish deeds. With a genuine intention to bring back his dear brother, he pleaded Rama to accept his apologies on behalf of his mother and return to the kingdom to adorn the throne. But Bharata had to be satisfied with the wooden sandals of Rama to take back to the kingdom as his representative to be placed on the  throne and with a depressed heart, agreed to attend to the  administration as a caretaker government only till the return of Rama. Bharata was disappointed at his failure to bring back Rama. Therefore, he did not want to enter Ayodhya, where Rama was to be crowned. He established his government in the outskirts of the city, in a place called Nandigrama. He gave the honour of the king to the wooden sandals of Rama by placing them on the throne. Before finalising vital administrative decisions, he would reverentially place the proposals before the sandals for approval and permission for their execution, as it were.

            No sooner had the three begun the life of a recluse, they were faced with a train of difficulties which was to continue till the end of their exile. It all started with Shurpanakha, the sister of the ten headed Ravana. During her demonaic roamings in the forest, she was fascinated by the handsome personality of Rama. She made sinister advances to him which annoyed Lakshmana. On top of her misbehaviour, she humiliated Sita with insults couched in foul language. In order to punsh her, Lakshmana cut off her nose and ears. Shurpanakha wanted to avenge this cruelty and went straight to her brother Ravana prodding him to think of a suitable revenge, if he really had any affection for her. Ravana's pride was now challenged and his think tank was switched on.



Tosakanth sculpture of Ravana Thailand

             Ravana was endowed with everything one could aspire for in life. His erudition was enormous but trained for immoral utilisation. He reigned the prosperous island of Lanka. He had conquered Indra and Kubera, his own brother. His lustful nature had subjected countless, helpless married  women to become residents of his large harem. Brahma had blessed him with a life that could not be harmed by any power except that of man. [May be it was for this reason, Vishnu was born as Rama, a human being, to vanquish the evil in the form of Ravana]. Consumed by the arrogance of opulence, he challenged even the existence of God. There was no concept of soul in his life. He believed the life of a man ends with his death. Therefore, his outlook to life was, 'make hay while the sun shines'. We live today and there is no tomorrow. This kind of mindset justifies his heinous actions, heedless of merits or sins. He lived in a world of illusion and delusion. Valmiki describes the existence of Ravana as living for death.

            Ravana wanted to abduct Sita with the help of Maricha. Maricha tried to dissuade him for he had had a taste of Rama's power in the past. But Ravana threatened him with the order 'do or die'. Maricha as the deceptive golden deer lured Rama away from Sita who wanted to have it. Lakshmana was also sent away by Sita on hearing the names of Lakshmana and Sita called out by the dying Maricha, deceitfully in a voice resembling that of Rama. She feared Rama to be in distress. At this opportune moment, Ravana, as a rishi, approached Sita in the hut for alms and carried her away in his aerial chariot. The tragedy with Ravana was that he could not forcibly indulge in immoral violations with any woman due to a curse. Such an action would mean death to him. He put her in Ashokavana in his kingdom with rakshasis trying to influence her in favour of Ravana. They tried to convince Sita about Ravana's greatness being incomparable to that of her powerless husband Rama who had meekly lost the throne to his brother.

            Rama, in the course of his search for his beloved wife, found the vulture Jatayu lying fatally wounded. From him, Rama got the clue that Ravana had abducted Sita. In the process of saving Sita from the demon, Jatayu was struck. Further proceeding to Kishkinda, Rama made an alliance with Sugriva, the king of the monkeys. He agreed to send out his army of monkeys on a search expedition. Efficient Hanuman, the ardent devotee of Rama, was sent in the southern direction. He located Sita in the Ashokavana in Lanka.The presentation of Rama's ring to Sita was a symbol of his identity as Rama's emissary. It was necessary to convince the already harrassed lady that Hanuman was not Ravana in disguise. He assured her of speedy deliverance from the monstrous Ravana by Rama's contingent.To make known to Ravana that he had come on behalf of Rama, he tried to damage the natural beauty of Lanka. He killed some of the henchmen of Ravana who had been sent to tackle the monkey whose power of strength was under estimated by the demons. After a stiff fight, Hanuman allowed himself to be bound and presented before Ravana. The demon unwisely issued orders to set fire the monkey's tail. Hanuman was infuriated as the tail is the pride of monkeys. In turn, Hanuman burnt a large part of Lanka to show what havoc his burning tail could create.  Hanuman, as an ambassador, requested Ravana to return Sita to Rama if he wanted to save his own life. But Ravana was adamant to fight against Rama. When Vibheeshana, his youngest brother, tried to advise him against punishing Hanuman who had come with a message of peace, he was miserably insulted. As a result, Ravana lost the support of Vibheeshana who joined Rama against his own brother. Vibheeshana was a righteous person who could not encourage evil. Even Kumbhakarna persuaded his brother against an immoral confrontation. The effort also turned to be futile. He, however, remained with Ravana to sacrifice his life for him.

            Happy with his discovery, Hanuman was pleased with his retaliation to give a sample of the power of Rama and his supporters to Ravana. He returned to his Lord with the wonderful tidings of success of his mission. Choodamani, the heirloom of the Dasharatha dynasty, was sent by Sita through Hanuman as a reminder to her husband to uphold the dignity of the family and not allow it to slip away into the hands of the demon.Moreover, she conveyed her unshakable determination to end her life if Rama failed to rescue her within the deadline drawn by Ravana. Rama immediately set out to wage war, enraged by the immoral manner in which Ravana had behaved towards his dear wife. With the assistance of the monkeys, a bridge was built across the ocean. Rama won the great battle against the demons, when he killed Ravana with his Brahmastra. He made Vibheeshana, his faithful ally, the king of Lanka.

  

Preparing for Lanka seige, and the Lanka Battle

          In the Uttarakanda of the Ramayana, which is considered to be an interpolation, Sita was banished by Rama to silence those indulging in maligning the character of Sita and ridiculing Rama as a hen pecked husband, readily accepting a woman who had lived in another man's house. Taking refuge in Valmiki's hermitage, Sita gave birth to the twins Lava and Kusha whom she was carrying at the time of banishment. Valmiki is believed to have trained them to recite his great epic, the Ramayana. Their song of the story of Rama at Rama's court revealed their identity. Sita was summoned to the court when she was again asked to prove her purity of character before everybody. Mother earth, from where Sita had emerged, came to her rescue to prove Sita's chastity by carrying her back on a golden throne.

           Rama's incarnation concluded successfully, with the death of Ravana and the rescue of Sita from the demon. Rama endeared himself in the hearts of all people, before he returned to his abode in Vaikuntha. Both Vishnu and Mahalakshmi were satisfied over the successful execution of their plan to vanquish the evil demon Ravana.

            [Thus Valmiki's great epic ended. It is a narration of an ideal king with spotless name and fame. Rama is celebrated as the worshipful God, not only in India but in many places like Thailand, on the island of Bali in Indonesia, in Nepal and Cambodia.]              

 

 </body>
</story>