<story>
<body>Chapter 51: Salva

 

Salva was the friend of Shishupala and he had a hatred for the Yadus especially Krishna who had denied his friend of his prospective bride Rukmini. He had vowed to destroy the Yadavas and relieve the earth of these undesirable people. To carry out the resolve, Salva began to worship Shiva living on a handful of dust. After nearly a year, Shiva appeared with the offer of a boon. Salva asked for a chariot that could traverse the entire universe unhindered, strike terror in the hearts of the Yadavas, and also help him from succumbing to the attacks of the celestials, asuras, mortals, gandharvas, reptiles or rakshasas. Ordered by Shiva, the asura architect Maya created an iron chariot named Soubha, and gave it to Salva.
 

 Soubha the magic chariot
 
 Salva, still obsessed with the old enmity and prejudiced against the Yadus, started towards Dvaraka in his pleasure chariot. He poured weapons devastating the entire city and caused all conceivable miseries to the lives. Pradyumna, the heroic chariot warrior, came out in his chariot, not being able to bear the sufferance of his subjects. Pradyumna was able to overcome all the hallucinations created by Salva. The soldiers of Pradyumna were unable to aim directly at the chariot which altered its position at lightning speed by magic powers. Then, they decided to shoot the arrows straight at Salva, whether he could be spotted as a soldier or as an ordinary man. It was a war of one upmentship between the two resolute armies, each desiring to establish victory over both heaven and earth. 
 
Dumana, a minister of Salva, struck hard on Pradyumnas chest with an iron mace, which incapacitated him to fight further. His charioteer Daruka brought his master out of the battlefield to save his life. Pradyumna was disappointed at having to turn his back and told his charioteer that he should not have saved him. He said he was ashamed to face his people having lost in the battle. Daruka tried to explain to him that the charioteer as well as the master should be concerned about each other while fighting and rise to the occasion to act promptly when there is danger to life. He said since this was the shastric injunction, he could not abandon his master to die. But Pradyumna was insistent on going back to continue his fight against Dumana. Going close to him, Pradyumna aimed his eight arrows at the minister. Four of them killed his steeds, one took the life of his charioteer, two destroyed his bow and banner and the last one pierced through his head.
 
Krishna, at that time, away in Indraprastha for the Rajasuya, was returning to his city. Worried over the evil omens, he expected the partisan kings of Shishupala to have taken advantage of the absence of the two brothers and invaded Dvaraka. Seeing the despicable plight of his people, he left Balarama to guard the city, while he went to challenge Salva whom he located in his chariot Soubha. He warned his charioteer not to be afraid of the magician Salva who could assume forms at will, appear or disappear if he wished. Krishna sent a number of arrows against Salva and perforated his chariot in response to his powerful weapon shakti. When the bow sharnga of Krishna was struck by the enemy, it accidently slipped from his hand. Thrilled to see the weapon fall, Salva thought Krishna was staggering, unable to withstand his fierce attack. Salva shouted at Krishna for stealing his dear friends bride in public and also killing him in the assembly. Excited Salva said it was now his chance for victory, if Krishna could pick up courage to stand before him for a little while. He said he had the strength to tear to pieces Krishna's body whose invincible character he was so proud of. Krishna, in reply, said Salva's death was imminent. There was no meaning in boasting about his prowess unless he proved it in action. Krishna threw his mace with great velocity at Salvas collarbone and he began bleeding profusely. He suddenly disappeared when he had somewhat recovered from the blow.
 
Next moment, Krishna saw a person bowing at his feet who said he had been sent by Devaki. He informed Krishna about the capture of his father Vasudeva by Salva. For a split second Krishna was deep in thought. He was astonished, how a weak person like Salva could carry away his father when the strong muscular Balarama was standing on guard. He was depressed at the turn of destiny. While still sadly brooding about his fathers fate, he was once again taken by surprise. He saw Salva with a person in captivity whom he claimed to be Vasudeva. He threatened to kill him if Krishna did not act swiftly to save his father to whom he owed his birth. Hardly giving Krishna a moment to act, Salva cut the head of Vasudeva. With the head he rose up to the clouds on his chariot. Krishna was stunned in stupefaction when asura Maya came to inform him that it was only an illusory set up. Krishna then came out of the magic spell and found neither the messenger nor the headless trunk of his father. Krishna decided not to encourage Salvas tom foolery any further. With his mace he broke into pieces the chariot and the bow. His sudarshana chakra knocked down his kireeta [crown], kundala [ear-ring] and also his head.
 

         Salva slain

            [That the concept of aerial transport like the modern aeroplane existed in the ancient days is evident from the aerial chariot of Soubha of Salva, Pushpaka vimana of Ravana and that of Uparichara.]

 </body>
</story>