<story>
<body>Chapter 40: Pradyumna

 
 
 Kamadeva, cupid, the god of love, was reduced to ashes by the fiery third eye of Shiva. Kamadeva was another form of Vasudeva. Therefore he requested Krishna to restore his form and life. Krishna agreed and as a result he was born as Pradyumna, the son of Krishna and Rukmini. An asura by the name Samvara kidnapped the ten day old infant and threw him into the ocean. He was anticipating his death at the hands of the boy.
 

Pradyumna found in a fish belly
 
A fish swallowed the infant, which made its way to Samvaras kitchen. When the fish was cut, the child was found alive in its belly. Mayavati, popularly known as Rati, the wife of Kamadeva, adopted the child and reared him like her own son. As days went by, she began to visualise her husband in that child. This fact was substantiated by Narada who informed her of the infants life. She started treating the child reverentially as her husband Kama and the mother-son relationship ceased. Ratis unusual behaviour annoyed Pradyumna and he expressed his displeasure. Then Rati narrated his adventurous life. She told him how sorrowful it would have been for his mother Rukmini to lose her son. She advised him to act promptly to kill the asura who was a mayavi, possessing the power to take various forms at will. Rati taught Pradyumna the mahamayavidya, to counteract the asuras illusory power.
 
 Now well equipped to take up the asura, Pradyumna proceeded for a battle against him. There was a terrible fight between the two, each trying to score over the other. When Pradyumna threw his mace, the asura rose to the sky and began pelting stones from that height at his opponent. Floating in mid air, he tried to evade the counter attack. Pradyumna, after a prolonged fight, used the mahamayavidya against all the tactics of the asura and succeeded in killing him.
 
            Rati and Pradyumna, one day, entered the inner apartment at Dvaraka. The women hid themselves, feeling shy at the sudden entry of Krishna. Immediately they were able to see that the look alike person in their apartment was someone else and not their Lord. While they were puzzled about the identity of the man accompanied by a pretty woman, Krishna, Rukmini, Balarama, Vasudeva and Devaki entered. At the sight of the youth, Rukminis memories went back to her lost son Pradyumna. She thought her son would have been this boys age now if he had lived. As she continued to look at the boy, she saw a close resemblance to Krishna creating a strong feeling of the return of her long lost son. Arrival of Narada, at this juncture, cleared all doubts because Krishna, though he knew everything, maintained silence as if taking pleasure in the happenings. Narada gave a resum of the early life of Pradyumna. Rukminis joy was beyond words, at the safe return of her son.
Interesting Anecdotes

 
 


Kamadeva reduced to ashes by Shiva

  

             Kamadeva turned to ashes: Kamadeva was the second son of Dharma, one of the Prajapatis born of Brahma. He had two brothers, Shama and Harsha. Kama was the most handsome of the three. He became the god of love, passion and beauty.

            There are two stories about Kama being reduced to ashes by Shiva's wrath. Though the first story is linked to the second, the latter stands independent as an oft quoted popular legend in this regard. Brahma, the creator, fell in love with goddess Sarasvati, his own creation. Though he placed her on the tongue of each of his creation, he  made her his wife, being captivated by her beauty. Delayed realisation of his immoral action aroused his anger against Kamadeva for kindling passion in him. He cursed Kama to become a victim to the fiery anger of Shiva. But this curse was executed only later. To explain this delay, another story is linked to it.

            After the death of Sati, Shiva, determined not to marry again, retired to the Himalayas for observing rigorous penance. At that time, demon Taraka had become invincible by a boon that only the son of Shiva could slay him. He harassed the gods and became Indra by winning over the Indraloka. As lord of the gods, he was aware of Parvati's determination to marry none other than Shiva and that she was engaged in a deep penance for successful achievement of her goal. In an attempt to exploit his power and authority, Taraka arrogantly sent Kamadeva to distract Shiva in meditation. He commanded him to aim his arrows of passion towards Maheshvara, in favour of Parvati. Shiva was furious at the bold attempt of the god of love. As his normal pair of eyes were engrossed in meditation, he opened his third eye in the middle of his forehead. The flood of fire, emitting from his third eye, was shot at Kama, reducing him to ashes. Despite Rati's pleadings to restore the life of her husband, Shiva would not relent. So, he was destined to live forever without a physical form-ananga.</body>
</story>