<story>
<body>Sage king Anga of the Dhruva lineage was a pious man strictly observing the scriptural injunctions. He married Sunitha, daughter of Mrithyu. When Angas offerings were rejected by gods during the horse sacrifice, he acted on the advice of brahmanas to perform a sacrifice for the birth of a son. Subsequently, a son was born to him whom he named Vena. Unfortunately, he imbibed all the unrighteous qualities of his grand-father Mrithyu. Angas efforts to reform his son failed for he seemed to be incorrigible. In disgust, Anga left his palace in the dead of night and his whereabouts could not be traced. The kingdom without a ruler was plundered by robbers and dacoits. Insecurity had spread like wild fire. The brahmanas decided to make Vena the king. True to his nature, he turned out to be an undependable king. His wicked ways caused the earth to become barren of its fertility and prosperity. The arrogant king considered himself superior even to Lord Narayana by whose grace he was born. The brahmanas could not tolerate him and he died by their curse. Now the country continued to languish in unhappiness. Vena had died without a successor. The brahmanas used their yogic powers and brought a boy and a girl from the arms of the dead body of Vena. They were christened as Prithu and Archi. They were the forms of Lord Narayana and Goddess Lakshmi. As they represented the eternal divine couple, a marriage was possible between the siblings.
 

                                                                        Prithu and Archi
           
            Prithu was a righteous pious king. Despite his efforts to bring normalcy on earth, he witnessed only wide spread adversity and famine causing many hunger deaths He was angry with mother earth for swallowing the seeds and plants which caused crop failure in his kingdom. Therefore, he thought of destroying her to seek his revenge. Earth begged his mercy and said she had swallowed the herbs and plants to protect them from the wicked people. She asked Prithu to get a calf while she took the form of a cow. By milking her, the seeds and plants would flow out like milk. Since she would be the wish granting cow Kamadhenu, all gods could milk her to obtain things according to their desire. Prithu cheerfully acted as directed. With abundance of fertility and prosperity, suffering was completely forgotten as a bad dream.
 

Prithu chasing Prithvi, who took the form of a cow
 
            Prithu was, with all seriousness, engaged in the marathon performance of a hundred horse sacrifices. At the start of his hundredth sacrifice, Indra thought his supremacy would be lost if Prithu managed to complete the final one. He stole the sacrificial horse as an obstruction to the successful completion of the sacrifice. Prithus son, on the advice of sage Atri, retrieved the horse from Indra who could not deceive the boy by his disguise. Prithu aimed his arrow against Indra. Brahma wanted to avert the disaster that would follow. He advised the king to withdraw the arrow forthwith and also give up the last of his horse sacrifices. Brahma explained to Prithu, since he and Indra were the forms of the Supreme Lord, it was absurd to kill one another. It would amount to killing oneself. He told him that he had already equalized Indra by his ninety nine horse sacrifices. He further said that Prithu should, hereafter, endeavour to impress upon people about the value of virtue as against evil which is detrimental to spiritual development. Brahmas advice refined his mental outlook. His excellent governance based on Dharma is even today compared to that of Yudhishthira and his glories are sung as those of Lord Rama
 

Prithu withdraws horse sacrifice
against Indra
 

Interesting Anecdotes

 

Nishadas: The Nishadas belong to an aboriginal tribe, short and stunted, residing in the mountainous forests. In the Ramayana, Guha, a nishada chief ferried Rama across the Ganges in his boat. The story of the origin of this tribe is quite fascinating. Venas deplorable behaviour and his tormenting attitude towards the subjects, forced him into a premature death by the curse of the brahmanas. Without an heir to carry on the lineage of the noble king Anga, the brahmanas attempted to produce a successor by their yogic powers from the thighs of Vena. Much to their disappointment, a nishada emerged who was not eligible to be crowned as the king. In their next attempt, Prithu and Archi were born from his arms. But the brahmanas allowed the nishada to live and thus the tribe came into existence



Nishada Guha ferrying Rama

 

 </body>
</story>